<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The danger of being almost a Christian. Shewing, [brace] 1. How far men may go without grace. 2. Why some men go so far. 3. Why they go no farther. 4. The dangerous estate of such persons. / By John Chishull, minister of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Chishull, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 227 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 90 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79525</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3903</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1694_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209426</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868308</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868308</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170271</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79525)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170271)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 211:E1694[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The danger of being almost a Christian. Shewing, [brace] 1. How far men may go without grace. 2. Why some men go so far. 3. Why they go no farther. 4. The dangerous estate of such persons. / By John Chishull, minister of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Chishull, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 167, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Neile, for Francis Eglesfield, and are to be sold at the Marygold in Pauls Church-yard.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London: :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"1. How far .. such Persons." bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Jan: 26"; the 7 in the imprint date has been crossed out and replaced with a "6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Conversion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Protestant authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170271:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE DANGER <hi>OF BEING</hi> ALMOST a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>SHEWING,
<list>
                  <item>1. How far men may go without Grace.</item>
                  <item>2. Why ſome men go ſo far.</item>
                  <item>3. Why they go no farther.</item>
                  <item>4. The dangerous eſtate of ſuch Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>John Chiſhull,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Neile,</hi> for <hi>Francis Eglesfield,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Marygold in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170271:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170271:2"/>
            <head>To the Right VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull <hi>Peter Atkins,</hi> Mayor, <hi>John Blundel</hi> Eſq with the reſt of the Burgeſſes, Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and Inhabitants of <hi>Tiverton.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved in the Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHat reaſon You (above all others) have to read and conſider the things which I preſent to your view, the Introduction to, and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the truth laid before you will tell. I trust many of you are convinced that I carry
<pb facs="tcp:170271:3"/>you upon my heart, and that my deſign in this undertaking is only to engage your hearts more fully to God. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this account I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of your complyance with it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> have reckoned it amongst my choiceſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, that the Lord hath owned me in ſome meaſure amongst you, and hath made you to feel as wel as hear what I have ſpoken. Yet in the midst of my rejoycing for ſome, I have had ſad thoughts of heart for others, for whom I have ſometimes had great hopes, and again as great feares; Since I have known any thing of Preaching, (and indeed it is little that <hi>I</hi> yet know of it) <hi>I</hi> have Preach'd very much by what I have ſeen and known of your tempers and Conditions, and I can ſay (through Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) that my labour hath not been altogether in vain. I bleſs God that I can think on ſome of you with delight; the entertainment which you have given to the Word, and the gracious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mpreſſions which you carry upon your ſpirits, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are my rejoycing before the Lord. Yet give me
<pb facs="tcp:170271:3"/>leave to minde you, that the number of Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted ones is but ſmal in compariſon of thoſe Convinced ones which I have obſerved amongst you. Many have received the Word with trembling, others with joy; yet after ſuch ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings and ſtrong working of heart (which they could not conceal, have either grown cold again; or elſe have contented themſelves with a luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm profeſſion; This I can truly ſay hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated much of my former comfort; and ſo ſtrong have the impreſſions of theſe things been upon my ſpirit, that many ſad thoughts have riſen in me, that ſurely my labour is neer at an end in that place, and the Lord will call me off either by death (as he threatned of late) or ſome other way. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this conſideration I have been willing to liſten to thoſe who deſired that theſe few Sermons might be made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, that by this means th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y might lie before you, either to quicken you, or to accuſe you; that when you ſhall neither hear, nor ſee me, you may ſee in them how my heart ſtood affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you: and poſſibly the view of theſe lines
<pb facs="tcp:170271:4"/>may awaken the convictions which ſome of you have buried, the perſwaſions which in ſome are decayed, and the reſolutions which ſome of you have taken up for God, but not followed: Oh when this Book fals into any ſuch hands, (as doubtleſs ſuch it will meet withall) let me in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat thoſe herein concerned to ſuffer theſe two thoughts to dwel a little upon their hearts:</p>
            <p>First, that their hearing as wel as my preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing must come to judgement.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that Convictions ſlighted, Perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions not improved, Promiſes and purpoſes bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, will be the worst companions that you can carry to Hel with you; yet this <hi>I</hi> am aſſured of, that many of you cannot periſh but under the weight of many of theſe.</p>
            <p>I have obſerved two ways, in which eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the Devil couzens convinced ſouls.</p>
            <p>First, in the <hi>Time:</hi> he tels them it is too ſoon to be ſerio us in youth, another time will ſerve; thus many periſh under <hi>delaies.</hi> To prevent this evil, I preſented you formerly with
<pb facs="tcp:170271:4"/>a ſmal Treatiſe
<note n="*" place="margin">The Young Mans Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento.</note> which I hope hath ſatisfied you ſully of the folly and danger of delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he labours to deceive in the <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> of the change that is wrought; if he ſees that they will do ſomething, yea and that the ſoul is agreed upon the time, that it muſt be <hi>Now</hi> while it is called to day, then he ſtrives to limit them. Firſt, with Negatives. He tels them they are not as they were, and therefore all is wel. He tels them they are changed; and it may be true, though they are not made <hi>New.</hi> If they be civil or moral that were prophane and unrighteous, this he perſwades them is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much: but if he ſuffer them to put on a form of Religion, though it reach not the heart; then he aſſures them that their Reformation is ful in weight and meaſure heaped up, preſſed down, and running over; when all this time they are not come to the loweſt form of thoſe that are Chriſtians indeed. Now, knowing that
<pb facs="tcp:170271:5"/>ſome of you are reſolved to do ſomething, and fearing that you ſhould be deceived, and ſo do nothing to the purpoſe. I have laid theſe things before you, that you might be the better able to judge of the meaſure of your perſwaſions, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, and performances.</p>
            <p>And ſince I have undertaken to ſpeak to all, being affectionately willing to be ſerviceable to you all. Let me add a word to you that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to attend the publick Ministry in that place, to hear what hath been there delivered; yet poſſibly you will vouchſafe a private peruſal of theſe truths: If this little Tract comes into your hands, I beſeech you enquire ſeriouſly by it into the state of your ſouls; for I fear you have little cloſe convincing Preaching amongst You. O bethink your ſelves of former days, when you ſat under the Now deſpiſed Ministry in <hi>Tiver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> which ſome of you called the Ministry of Christ, and your ſelves the ſeals of it; You ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med then to have ſome ſenſe of the Quickneſs
<pb facs="tcp:170271:5"/>nnd Power of the Word; but how is it now? Are thefe Times better then thoſe? To what conſiderable height are you growen in Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity ſince you turned your backs upon thoſe Opportunities you once counted precious? Ah let me tel you, though you have deſerted me, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not caſt you out of my thoughts, hopes, and Prayers, truſting that the Lord will bring back ſuch as have ſet their faces to ſeek him in truth, as he hath done fome already, in anſwer to Prayer. Yet you know that I have loſt nothing by your leaving of me, but the opportunities of being further ſerviceable to your ſouls; and this indeed to me is a great loſſe; for if <hi>I</hi> know any thing of my heart, it is this, that <hi>I</hi> value my life by the advantages that I have of being helpfull to poore ſouls in the great things of God.</p>
            <p>It is an eaſie matter to draw up thoſe that have no grace to any form; and this were a poor low thing to make our interest. By this
<pb facs="tcp:170271:6"/>meanes it is as eaſie to ſtop young awakened ſouls before they come half way to Chriſtianity; it is my fear for many of you, that you are ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived no further then the forme; and my fear is as great that you will hinder others from going beyond it, by perſwading them into an opinion of themſelves, that they are Chriſtians, before they are, or know what it is to be ſuch.</p>
            <p>If this may prevent any of you from miſcarry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any way, I ſhal heartily bleſſe the Lord, and rejoyce to be alſo a helper of your Faith.</p>
            <p>Finally my friends of all ſorts, Lay what you have heard, or may hearread to the Word, &amp; your hearts to both, and judg faithfully in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Put it to the Queſtion whether you are Altogether Chriſtians or no, and reſolve to be ſuch, or to be nothing. Be in good earneſt with God, and cleave to him with ful purpoſe of heart. Oh fulfil my joy which you cannot more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably further then by a candid acceptance, and conſcientious improvement of what I here
<pb facs="tcp:170271:6"/>tender to you. That it may be everyway for your good, you ſhall have with it the Prayers of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your willing Servant, in the work of the Lord,</hi> Jo. Chiſhull.</signed>
               <dateline>London, <date>Jan. <hi>16. 1656.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170271:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170271:7"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACTS 26.28.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Almoſt thou perſwadeſt me to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. The Introduction.</head>
               <p>IT is not uſual with me to make Apologies for, or Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions to my Diſcourſes: but at this time I conceive it is convenient, if not neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſpeak ſomething of this nature. Though it be ſufficient warrant for me to pitch upon this portion which <hi>I</hi> have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, becauſe it is the word of the Lord, and the ſame conſideration is weighty to enjoyn your beſt attention; yet there is ſomething more, which hath ſwayed with me to take theſe words into my ſerious thoughts, and to preſent the reſult of them to you, which <hi>I</hi> hope when you have
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170271:8"/>weighed, they wil ſeem as additional ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to awaken your ſpirits, and you wil account your ſelves particularly enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to hear what <hi>I</hi> am ſo deeply ingaged to ſpeak. <hi>I</hi> had choſen another ſubject to treat upon, which <hi>I</hi> conceived might ſuit wel with that which <hi>I</hi> ſo lately finiſhed; but my reſolutions to proſecute that were changed by ſome impreſſions which the Lord made upon me in my late ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>That <hi>I</hi> was viſited with weakneſs, is known to you all; but how great it was, and how near to the grave it brought me, is known but to few. But in this, (which was the ſoareſt which <hi>I</hi> ever experienc'd,) yea in the very height and prevalency of it when my friends did many of them look upon me as under a ſentence of death, then was the Lord pleaſed</p>
               <p>Firſt, to give me a particular aſſurance of my recovery, from that ſcripture, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 118.17. <hi>Thou ſhalt not die, but live and declare the works of the</hi> LORD.</p>
               <p>Secondly, a particular knowledg of the time of my recovery, from <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.2. <hi>After two dayes I wil revive</hi> thee, <hi>in the third day I wil raiſe</hi> thee <hi>up, and</hi> thou <hi>ſhalt live in</hi> my <hi>ſight.</hi> All which <hi>I</hi> found exactly made good unto me to a day, according to the Word
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170271:8"/>of the Lord, which was then ſet upon my ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the Lord did not onely aſſure me of my life, but did alſo appoint me out my work, without which <hi>I</hi> account my life of very ſmal value. At that time when <hi>I</hi> was under a ſtrong Fever, and other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers which might very well be judged unfit companions for meditation; <hi>I</hi> ſay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the paines of my growing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, my thoughts were then drawn ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out to conſider of the ſtate and conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this place; and conſidering the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of it, <hi>I</hi> rankt them under three Heads.</p>
               <p>Frſt, ſome that minded not God, nor Religion, and that ſat unſhaken under the VVord.</p>
               <p>Secondly, ſome that <hi>I</hi> hope have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved it, and that do ſincerely deſire to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſuch as halt betwixt two opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that hang betwixt God and the world, that are wrought upon by the Word, and are under ſtrong convictions, and workings of ſpirit, but yet are not brought fully to cloſe with Chriſt; theſe are <hi>I</hi> am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not a few in this place. The ſerious conſideration of theſe did moſt of all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect my ſoul with pitty, and that pitty wrought in me ſtrong and earneſt deſire. It
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170271:9"/>grieved me to ſee ſo many ſouls like <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea, Rev.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Lukewarm,</hi> or like <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im, hal-fbaked, Hoſ.</hi> 7.8. it did not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle trouble my ſpirit to ſee ſo many perſons carry their convictions about them, as pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners dragg their chains after them: <hi>I</hi> am perſwaded if every perſon that hath been convine'd under the word in this place, and that hath had ſome kinde of perſwaſions to come in to Chriſt, and yet ſtands it out, had but a chain about his Legg, we ſhould hear a fearful ratling of iron when the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation moves. Thus was my ſoul grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for many of you; but my affections did not ſpend themſelves in pittying, but awakened my deſires, and <hi>I</hi> then caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout me how I might be ſerviceable to you, with that little inch of time that the Lord ſhould give me, even to you that ſeem at ſome times not to be far from the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>God,</hi> and yet if you go no farther, are never like to come there.</p>
               <p>While my thoughts were thus working, it pleaſed the Lord to ſet this portion of Scripture which I have read unto you upon my ſpirit, in which I ſaw your condition exactly preſented in <hi>Agrippa.</hi> But this word it ſelf was not barely brought home to me, but the Lord gave in then to my thoughts thoſe things which I have to deliver to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170271:9"/>you, ſo that I may ſafely ſay, that hee put the word into my mouth; for what I have now to deliver, both for the doctrine, and all the particulars, relating to explain and confirm it, were penn'd when <hi>I</hi> was unable to govern a pen; they were framed in my greateſt weakneſs, &amp; taken from my mouth by a Friend that came to viſit me.</p>
               <p>Theſe things I mention to you, that you may be perſwaded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, to paſſe by any thing of weakneſs in this diſcourſe, knowing it was compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the midſt of weakneſs, and that <hi>I</hi> aim not to commend my ſelf to you, but to preſent your conditions before you, and that with all manner of plaineſs.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that if you meet with any thing uſeful &amp; ſeaſonable, you would g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve the glory to God; if the Word me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t with any of your ſouls, ſay, the Lord hath met with me this day; if it hit as right as <hi>Davids</hi> ſtone did, and ſtick in your foreheads, know <hi>I</hi> threw it as he did, not by skil, but by Faith; it is the Lord that guided my hand. If any ſay, Can all that which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in ſeveral ſermons be the product of a few houres meditation? I anſwer, that I can ſay without faining what <hi>Jacob</hi> offered to excuſe his haſty dinner for his Father, <hi>Gen.</hi> 27 20. <hi>The Lord brought it unto my h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170271:10"/>
               <p>Thirdly, to ſhew you what ſpecial and peculiar reaſon ſome of you have to attend diligently to what ſhall be ſpoken ô you cannot but ſee a finger in the margent bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding you obſerve, and the hand of God pointing at ſome of you; for though he ſpeaks in every word, yet more eſpecially in ſuch as he ſends by ſpecial meſſengers, or directs to us by ſingular and remarkable providences. Now there are two things which ſhould ſtir you up to liſten to this word, as not being of common and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry conſideration.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that one is raiſed from the dead to ſpeak to you.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that this word was put into his mouth, eſpecially for your ſakes, ſo that he can ſay, that this work which he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this day, is part of his great errand, for which the Lord ſent him back again to this place.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that you may know that I have you upon my heart in all conditions, in ſickneſſe as wel as in health, in life and in death. But if none of theſe things move you, know that God will raiſe up <hi>Nineveh</hi> in judgement againſt you, who repented at his word, whom God had brought from the grave. Nay the rich man in hell will come againſt you, who perſwaded himſelf
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170271:10"/>that his brethren would repent if one from the dead were ſent unto them; and that which is worſe, the Lord who hath now raiſed me up for you, will raiſe me up to condemn you; yea this word which <hi>I</hi> now preach to you, ſhall be terrible, and you ſhal not be able to ſtand before it in the day of the Lord.</p>
               <p>This is ſufficient (and to ſome may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more then enough) to my preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of handling the words. Now to the occaſion of the words themſelves as they lie in the Text.</p>
               <p>The riſe of theſe words is evident to be from <hi>Paul</hi> his diſcourſe, of which we have a full account in this Chapter.</p>
               <p>The ſubſtance of his ſpeech was to defend himſelf againſt the accuſations of the Jews before <hi>Agrippa, Feſtus,</hi> the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and <hi>Bernice,</hi> with others that ſate as Judges betwixt him and the Jews. The ſpeech hath three principal Heads.</p>
               <p>Firſt, an account of his life, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of his zeal againſt the chriſtians before his converſion, from <hi>v.</hi> 4. to 13.</p>
               <p>Secondly, his wonderful converſion, <hi>ver.</hi> 13.18.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, his practice and profeſſion af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, <hi>v.</hi> 19.23.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170271:11"/>
               <p>We have next conſiderable the iſſue of his ſpeech, it wrought variouſly upon his Judges.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Feſtus</hi> deemed him mad, yet he thought his madneſs was not common; he judged it to be alearned madneſs; not being able to entertaine the Doctrines which he preacht of the Reſurrection, nor to credit the ſtory which <hi>Paul</hi> told of his converſion, he thought that theſe were but clouds and fancies of his brain which was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrought.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Agrippa</hi> is of another mind and receives more candidely, though he do not digeſt fully what <hi>Paul</hi> had ſaid; he ſeems to be ſo far convict of the truth, that he is upon the turning point, ready to come over to <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, the whole Councel took ſuch impreſſions from his diſcourſe, that they all agree that <hi>Paul</hi> is innocent, <hi>verſ.</hi> 30, 31.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This ſhews us the coherence of theſe words with the former, and it refers us either to <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpeech, or to <hi>Feſtus;</hi> if we conſider it as relating to the firſt, then it ſhews us the ground of <hi>Agrippa</hi>'s perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170271:11"/>
               <p>If to the <hi>latter,</hi> then it helps to heighten his perſwaſion, and to ſhew us how ſtrong it was and hot at the preſent. <hi>Then, (viz.)</hi> when <hi>Agrippa</hi> had conſidered of what <hi>Paul</hi> had ſpoken, either in his firſt ſpeech which was to all the Council, although di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected more eſpecially to him, <hi>ver.</hi> 2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Now if we conſider theſe perſwaſions in <hi>Agrippa</hi> to ariſe from <hi>Pauls</hi> general ſpeech, it will according to the parts of it afford us theſe Obſervations: Firſt, from the relation of <hi>Pauls</hi> former courſe of life.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Obſervation.</hi> That when the Lord makes great and viſible changes upon open and violent enemies of his ways, he cauſes much of conviction to fall upon the ſpirits of conſidering perſons; for they which conſult with reaſon, muſt needs conclude that there muſt be ſome remarkable thing, ſomething of weight that muſt cauſe ſuch a change.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſerv.</hi> 2. The diſcovering of the way the change is wrought in, is as uſefull and convincing as the change it ſelf. <hi>Paul</hi> thought it no idle ſtory to tell them how God brought him over, as well as that he had done it. This may ſerve to juſtifie the practices of thoſe who deſire to know the way of Gods working upon ſouls
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170271:12"/>in the bringing them over to Chriſt, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how demonſtrative this is of the work of grace, beyond a bare profeſſing that <hi>I</hi> do believe, or repent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> 3. From the account that <hi>Paul</hi> gives of his after-practice, that boldneſſe in living up to the truths we are convinc'd of, does make much for the convincing of ſuch as yet have not received the truth. This argued that there vvas ſomething of re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in that relation which he made of his change, and the manner, which at firſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring might ſeem ridiculous, and incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. They who conſidered how <hi>Paul</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the truth in practiſe, and with what hazard he profeſt it, might conceive that his converſion was no dream.</p>
               <p>Again, vve may refer theſe words to <hi>Pauls</hi> particular ſpeech mentioned <hi>v.</hi> 26, 27. directed in part to <hi>Feſtus,</hi> and in part to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grippa,</hi> in which he takes the advantage of defending himſelf both againſt his general charge by the Jews, and the particular im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation put upon him by <hi>Feſtus, v.</hi> 24. and this he does by taking hold of two things, which did much conduce to his preſent purpoſe.</p>
               <p>The firſt was <hi>Agrippa</hi>'s general know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of cuſtomes, and memorable ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, and eſpecially of the truth of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170271:12"/>of fact related, and queſtioned, yea cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by <hi>Feſtus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Agrippa</hi>'s general aſſent unto the things contained in the ſcriptures, <hi>v.</hi> 27. Theſe things being hand ſomly couched in a wiſe and inſinuating appeal, draw out this profeſſion from him, <hi>Then ſaid Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa unto Paul, Almoſt thou perſwadeſt me to be a Chriſtian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From hence obſerve;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> 1. It is a great advantage for a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, when the people he is to deal withal have ſome principles laid beforehand for him to faſten his word unto. This was the advantage that <hi>Paul</hi> had upon <hi>Agrippa,</hi> more then upon the reſt of his Judges, and therefore he applies himſelf moſt to him, and with good ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> 2. There muſt be much wiſdome and prudence mixt with the diſpenſing of the Goſpel, to know vvhen, and how, and to vvhom to ſpeak, and to eſpie out every little thing that might further or facilitate our vvork; this vvas the craft which <hi>Paul</hi> mentions, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.16. <hi>Being crafty I caught you with guile.</hi> He ſaw <hi>Agrippa</hi> vvas the fitteſt perſon to work upon, and he eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied what vvas in him to lay hold of, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſixes moſt upon this mark.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſ.</hi> 3. A word of commendation and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170271:13"/>encouragement ſometimes given to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, gains much reſpect to the truth it ſelf. Thus we finde that applauſe which <hi>Paul</hi> gave to <hi>Agrippa,</hi> he returns to the truth which he profeſt, and declares himſelf al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt overcome with the Majeſty and ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of it, which ſhined ſo gloriouſly in the Apoſtles Narrative. Theſe things the connexion of the Text with its dependance upon <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpeech affords us. We may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it alſo as relating ſomething to <hi>Feſtus</hi> his cenſure upon <hi>Pauls</hi> diſcourſe. <hi>Then ſaid Agrippa, (viz.)</hi> when <hi>Feſtus</hi> had but now calumniated the truth which was held forth, and had judged <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine and Relation to be but a learned madneſs, then <hi>Agrippa,</hi> ſtands up to wipe off the reproach which he caſt upon the truth. If we conſider it with theſe circumſtances of the time and place, when the Goſpel had been cenſured ſo lately by a potent man, and a ruler, and in the preſence of the Jews who were the Apoſtles accuſers, and ſtrong enemies of the word he had delivered: Then and there, for <hi>Agrippa</hi> to make ſuch a Declaration as this in favour of the truth, was much; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering it thus, we may obſerve,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſervation.</hi> Firſt, the Lord doth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times provide ſome to ſtand up for the truth and the Profeſſors of it in greateſt ſtraits,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170271:13"/>who yet never receive it themſelves.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we may here ſee what great convictions do fall upon the ſpirits of ſome men, who yet are never ſavingly wrought upon. It muſt needs be conceived, that the impreſſions were ſtrong upon <hi>Agrippa</hi>'s ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that they extorted from him ſuch an open profeſſion as this is, at ſuch a time and in ſuch a place. But this truth will come more fully under our conſideration from the words themſelves; only this circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance may give ſome light to that which lies ſo open in the Text it ſelf.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The Doctrine propounded with the general proof of it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE have then in the words three things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the impreſſion which <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine made upon <hi>Agrippa;</hi> it wrought by way of perſwaſion, <hi>Thou perſwadeſt me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, The object of this perſwaſion, that is, embracing and profeſſing the goſpel of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the meaſure of this perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Almoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170271:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Almoſt,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in <hi>parvo,</hi> in a little, or ſomething <hi>I</hi> ſhould be a Chriſtian vvith thee. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems to take him in this ſence, when he wiſhes that he vvere as he, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> not onely in little, but in much; not onely in ſome things, but in all.</p>
               <p>Some read it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, thou haſt perſwaded me in a little time, or by a ſhort ſpeech to be a Chriſtian. Some tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters render it by <hi>Propemodum,</hi> and ours fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them, and it is very ſafe, almoſt or vvithin a little thou perſwadeſt me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Perſwadeſt me,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> it ſignifies both <hi>ſuadere, &amp; perſuadere,</hi> either to uſe meanes to bring a man to our opinion, or practice by arguments and exhortations, or elſe to prevail upon the party, and bring him to what we deſire.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Sometimes it is taken for exhorting and reaſoning only, <hi>Acts</hi> 18.4. <hi>He reaſoned in the ſynagogue every ſabbath, and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Jews, and the Greeks.</hi> This was <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantis potius quam efficientis;</hi> he endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vvhat he did not effect: but this could not be the ſenſe of <hi>Agrippa</hi> here, for <hi>Paul</hi> had uſed no particular exhortation to him.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170271:14"/>
               <p>Secondly, it ſignifies to prevaile upon, and to bring'a perſon to reſt in what vve ſay, and ſo is taken here; for it muſt needs note the influence that <hi>Pauls</hi> diſcourſe had upon <hi>Agrippa,</hi> inſomuch that it brought him to aſſent unto what he ſaid, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe himſelf even almoſt ready to joyn with him in profeſſing the ſame things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To be a Chriſtian,</hi> that is, to become a Diſciple and follower of Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>I</hi> ſhal preſent you with my thoughts of theſe words as they were preſented to me in our Tranſlation, and as we read them, they afford this Obſervation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obſerv.</hi> That men may be almoſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and yet never true Chriſtians; they may be almoſt ſuch in reſpect of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion who wil never be ſuch in reſpect of their practice and performance.</p>
               <p>In handling the Doctrinal Obſervation which <hi>I</hi> have propounded, <hi>I</hi> ſhal</p>
               <p>Firſt, lay down ſomething for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral proof of this.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>I</hi> ſhal particularly open and illuſtrate it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>I</hi> ſhal apply it:</p>
               <p>That this is a truth, is clear from many inſtances and examples in the Scripture. How far did <hi>Saul</hi> go, the firſt King of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> (<hi>I</hi> wiſh he had been the laſt example of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170271:15"/>this truth) he bid fairer for Heaven then many do that have ſtrong confidence of it. He ſeemed to be good among good men, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.10. he propheſied among the Prophets, he ſeems to be good by way of ſingularity; he oppoſes ſin when the whole ſtream ran againſt him, and ſeems excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding tender of the ſins of others, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.33, 34. yea he ſeems to be ſo zealous againſt ſin y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he would not ſpare his dear <hi>Jonathan,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.44. there was 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.6. ſuch a change upon him as was viſible, and made him another man, yea this change was ſo deep, that it reached to the very heart of him; it is ſaid 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.9. God gave him <hi>another heart,</hi> yet this vvas not a thorow change, he had not a <hi>new</hi> heart, though <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother</hi> heart; neither was <hi>Saul</hi> a <hi>new</hi> man, though <hi>another</hi> man.</p>
               <p>The young man in the Goſpel may be brought as a clear &amp; pregnant teſtimony of this truth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.20. ſee how far he went; he obſerved all the commands of God, and not willing to ſtop here, he profeſſes his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to know and do more yet: <hi>What lack I yet?</hi> this man went ſo far, that Chriſt himſelf ſayes of him that he vvas not far from the kingdom of God; yet ſo near a she came to it, he never reaches it.</p>
               <p>To this you may add the three ſorts of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170271:15"/>bad hearers, which are condemned by Chriſt, under the notion of bad ground, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.12, 13, 14. the worſt of the three did more then barely hear the word; they did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, and that into their hearts; for it is ſaid of the ſtony ground vvhich vvas worſt of the three, that the devil took the word, (not before it came at their hearts) but out of their hearts; he did not take their hearts away, ſo that they minded not what was ſpoken, as he doth many mens and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens, but he took it away after they had received it. Both the other go thus far, and ſomewhat farther; for their reception of the word is noted with ſome additional cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, as the ſecond received it with joy, and did not loſe it preſently, til in tract of time cares and pleaſures choaked it; the third yet exceeded both theſe, for it received, kept &amp; improved the Word, inbrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging forth ſome fruits, only it was not to perfection. If all this be not ground enough to build this concluſion upon, look to the fooliſh Virgins, and ſee how far they go in this point, and how like they vvere to the wiſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.1, 2, 3, 4, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Firſt, as for their profeſſion, it was viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they had Lamps in their hands.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this vvas not an ignorant pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion neither, for they had oyl in their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170271:16"/>Lamps, ſome illumination, and ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victions to keep this profeſſion alive.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, their profeſſion was not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out practice, intimated in theſe expreſſions,</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>They went:</hi> they were upon ſome motion, they did perform ſome duties, and obſerve Ordinances.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>They went forth, (viz.)</hi> they left many behind them, they went out from that condition of life in which they had lived, and they took up another courſe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they aſſociated themſelves with thoſe who did in truth fear God; they <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied the wiſe Virgins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, they complyed with their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and profeſt themſelves the followers of Chriſt, they went <hi>to meet the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, they did in every thing behave themſelves ſo like the wiſe Virgins, that they were not diſcerned, nor ſuſpected by the wiſe Virgins; the coming of Chriſt firſt detected them.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, their confidence held out unto the very laſt; for when the Bridegroom came they roſe to trim their Lamps, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to go in with the other, but were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, there was nothing wanting but
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170271:16"/>that which was inviſible, <hi>viz. oyl in their veſſels:</hi> they wanted grace in their hearts, and therefore though theſe came thus nigh to the very door of Heaven, and cry <hi>Lord, Lord open to us,</hi> yet it is in vain; Chriſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers them as ſtrangers, <hi>I know you not;</hi> if there needed any thing more to make this propoſition clear, <hi>I</hi> could inſtance in <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Demas,</hi> and others who went beyond theſe alſo, being not onely profeſſors, but preachers of the truth to others. But it is needleſs to inſiſt longer upon the proof of that vvhich the many ſad experiences and examples of our preſent age hath made ſo manifeſt. How many hath this Age brought forth of this kind, who have climbed high in profeſſion, but have fallen from the moſt viſible glorious appearance of godlineſs to the moſt abominable prophaneſſe, to be as conſcientiouſly vile as ever they were ſtrict. This ſhal ſerve for the general proof, by which you may ſee that this is a truth which <hi>I</hi> have propounded.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The Doctrine more particularly explained.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat this may be the better underſtood <hi>I</hi> ſhall make enquiry into theſe two things.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170271:17"/>
               <p>Firſt, what kind of perſwaſions men may have, which yet are not gracious.</p>
               <p>Secondly, from whence theſe do ariſe; and in this I ſhal conſider two things.</p>
               <p>Firſt, whence it is that they extend ſo far.</p>
               <p>Secondly, why they reach no farther.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, what kind of perſwaſions theſe are, which yet prove not effectual to the bringing men over to Chriſt, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to ſhew you firſt what Perſwaſion is: a perſwaſion is a morral bending of the judgement or will to truth, or goodneſſe, which are their proper objects, whether they be real or apparent; it is ſometimes taken for the inclining of the judgement, the bringing of any one to reſt in what we ſay; ſo it ſignifies as much as conviction of a truth; and if this be very ful and clear, then it imports as much as aſſurance; ſo it is taken, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38. <hi>I am perſwaded,</hi> that is I am aſſured, <hi>that nothing ſhal be able to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate us from the love of God which is in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord.</hi> I do not heſitate or doubt at all about this: thus it reſpects the underſtanding and judgement.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it is taken (and that moſt commonly) for the working over the Will to ſome duty or deſigne, either good in it ſelf, or made ſo to appear; thus it is uſed,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170271:17"/>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 13.43. and <hi>chap.</hi> 18.13. and ſo in this place<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This perſwaſion reſted in the Will, and had for its end, Action, following of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>In the firſt ſenſe <hi>Man</hi> may be ſaid to perſwade; the underſtanding and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment lie more open and naked, and one mans reaſon does give light to anothers.</p>
               <p>But in the ſecond (if we take it in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the chief good) it is <hi>Gods</hi> preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive only to perſwade; he only can penetrate the Will, and turn it to its proper object, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 110.3. <hi>In the day of thy power thy people ſhal be willing.</hi> Therefore <hi>Noah</hi> praying for, or propheſying of <hi>Japhets</hi> condition, ſays thus, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.27. The Lord perſwade <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and he ſhal dwel in the tents of Shem:</hi> we read it ordinarily, <hi>The Lord enlarge Japhet,</hi> but it may be as wel rendered, perſwade him. The word is <hi>Japht, of Patach, aperuit,</hi> it ſignifies properly to open a thing, and Metaphorically to perſwade, becauſe the heart muſt be opened in perſwading. Now when <hi>Noah</hi> prays that the Gentiles which came of <hi>Japhet</hi> ſhould be brought into the Church, which was to be ſetled in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of <hi>Shem,</hi> he prays that God would open their hearts, and effectually perſwade them, for he was onely ſufficient<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in this matter.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170271:18"/>
               <p>But to come nearer to the buſineſſe in hand, vve are to conſider what kind of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions unregenerate men may have; if we look to the firſt kind for thoſe which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the underſtanding and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, they may go very far, and ſo far, that they may ſeem not only <hi>almoſt,</hi> but <hi>altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Chriſtians. The judgement and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon may be for God, and may aſſent to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that is good, when the Will is for nothing that is good. As for example <hi>I</hi> ſhal enumerate ſome particulars.</p>
               <p>Firſt, they may be perſwaded of the evil of their own vvayes; this the very Gentiles knew vvho had not the Law. God had left them ſo much light that aroſe and accuſed them when they did evil, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15. it ſtood up in the place of God, and cenſured their abominations; if thoſe who had no Law, had yet an accuſer; ſurely then much more thoſe who have both Law and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel cannot but have ſome ſecret intimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and checks with ſome gripings of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience when they break out into ſuch ſins vvhich the light of nature, and the Word of the Lord do ſo palpably condemn, <hi>I</hi> am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that the Drunkard, Swearer, Lyer, Sabbath-breaker, the man that neglects Prayer, Reading, and Meditation, do not think theſe wayes of theirs are good; they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170271:18"/>vvalk up and down as ſelf-condemned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p>Secondly, they may ſee not onely the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil of their vvayes, but alſo the danger of them; they have ſome glances and hints, yea and ſometimes foretaſts of the ſad end of theſe things. They are convinct of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable and juſt connexion that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ſin and miſery; they ſee that they are going down to the chambers of death, and that their ſteps take hold of hell, and yet this vvill not ſtop them, they vvill have their luſts how dear ſoever they pay for them hereafter. This is evident, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.32. <hi>Who knowing the juſt judgement of God, that they who do ſuch things are worthy of death, not onely do the ſame, but have pleaſure in them that do them.</hi> There are three things lie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to them.</p>
               <p>Firſt, The judgement of God, that there is ſuch a judgement or ſentence pronounc'd againſt ſuch ſinners.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that this ſentence vvas unto death.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that this vvas a juſt and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous judgement, theſe things muſt needs car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry vvith them very great convictions of the demerit of ſin, and the danger of the ſinner.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, they may be perſwaded of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170271:19"/>neceſſity of a change; this muſt needs ariſe from the two former: he that ſees the evil of his own wayes, together with the danger of them, muſt needs conclude that a change muſt paſſe upon him in order to happineſs; though no unregenerate man does know what that change is which he muſt ſuffer if he wil be ſaved; yet many of them know thus much, that they muſt be changed; they are convinct that ſomething is to be done for Heaven, though they are ignorant of the particulars. I have met with ſome that have confeſſed that they could not read or think of that paſſage of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 3.3. <hi>(Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a man be born again, he cannot inherit the kingdom of God,)</hi> but it would perplex their thoughts; thus there is (<hi>I</hi> am perſwaded) in many men a confuſed general notion of Regeneration, though they have not a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct knowledge of it, and they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd it is a work which they have not yet experienc'd, without vvhich they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaved. <hi>I</hi> need not go out of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation for the proof of this: <hi>I</hi> am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident this is the perſwaſion of many of you, who know you muſt be changed, if ſaved: the Lord grant you may not carry theſe convictions to hell.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, they may be convinc'd of the equity of the wayes of God, and the reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rableneſs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170271:19"/>of all his commands, yea and of his judgments. How many are there whoſe affections ſerve the devil, and their luſts? who vvil notwithſtanding conſent in their judgements to the vvayes of God; they wil grant vvhen they are urged to it, that there is nothing more equitable then that the creature ſhould be conformed to the vvil of the Creator, &amp; that he that made us ſhould expect from us a ſubmiſſion to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, ſeeing vve depevd upon him, and vve ſhould improve and ſpend all that for him, which we receive from him. The ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry principles of Reaſon wil condemn the ſinner as a monſter, and the moſt irregular perſon in the vvorld, vvho would live with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being accountable to God upon whom he depends; this is to blot out the notion of a creature out of his heart; for vvhat reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable being could expect this, unleſs he were of himſelf, and could ſubſiſt without any help from another? if you propoſe this to the reaſon of many men, they wil confeſs it is very equitable that the Lord who made us, and by vvhoſe patience and bounty we ſubſiſt, ſhould put the yoak upon us, and that it is no injuſtice nor exaction in him to require the ſtricteſt obedience in us, ſo that vvhen he conſide rany or all the ways which the Lord preſcribes unto us to walk
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170271:20"/>towards him, though hee apprehend them as hard and unpleaſant thorough his weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and corruption, yet when he doth but glance upon the ſoveraigne power of God over his creatures, and the dependance of the creatures upon him, he muſt needs ſay, that it is a reaſonable thing, and juſt to fear this God, and to ſubmitt to all that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. And as they are convinc'd of the equity and juſtneſs of all his commands to us; ſo they are from hence forced to ſee the juſtice of that ſentence, which ſhal be pronounced againſt all thoſe that deſpiſe and refuſe the yoke of the Lord, as I hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before from that of <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.32. For what is more deeply rooted in nature then this Principle that the work ſhould praiſe the workman; and that the workman ſhould draw forth his own honour and glory from his own? and if theſe ſhall refuſe to ſerve the ends of their being, that then he ſhould ſubſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ract all comfortable influences from them, and turne his hand againſt them for evill. Now if theſe thinges be ingrafted in nature, ſurely men who have many acceſſions of light to their naturall principles by the goſpel under which they live, will goe to hell with a conviction of the equitie of thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hings which the Lord required of them and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170271:20"/>of the Iudgment which he hath paſt upon them.</p>
               <p n="5">V. They may be perſawded of the truth of the threatnings and promiſes; ſo that they may be able ſometimes to looke into heaven and hell through the truth of God in the one, and the other Thus Balaam ſaw the reality of thoſe promiſes which <hi>God</hi> had made to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and he ſaw alſo the certainty of the fulfilling of all that <hi>God</hi> had ſpoken againſt the enemies thereof: thus the eyes of wicked men are ſometimes opened, eſpecially of temporary beleevers and ſuch as are almoſt chriſtians, that they are cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convinc'd that there will be a difference betwixt thoſe that fear the Lord, and thoſe that fear him not; they know it will goe ill with the wicked; but it will goe well with the godly; ſo that when the threats denounced againſt ſuch are opened, they tremble as <hi>Faelix</hi> did at the preaching of judgement to come, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.25, They feel ſomething of what is threatned already in their conſciences; the word is as hot as an oven to them, which ſcorches them; &amp; convictions and terrors which from thence fall upon them are like ſtreams of fire brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out of hell it ſelf; ſo that if we did but ſome times obſerve, and conſider the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions that are made upon ſuch mens
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170271:21"/>ſpirtis, it would put it out of doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be a hell or not; and men vvould conclude that the dreadful things threatned in the Word of God are not ciphers, or things to be played vvithal, or the inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of men, onely to keep others in awe, as ſome Atheiſts have believed, but that they are truths whereof one tittle ſhal not fall to the ground unperformed; theſe things vvicked men know to be true here, and ſhal feel them true hereafter; yea theſe taſtes of the truth of the threatnings make often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times great viſible changes in them, and they do much to eſcape the judgement writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; thus <hi>Herod</hi> did many things when he heard <hi>John Baptiſt;</hi> and the Jews being terrified with the ſharpneſſe of his Miniſtry, came to him confeſſing their ſins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6. What ſays he to them, <hi>You generation of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, who hath warned you to flee from the wrath to come?</hi> as if he had ſaid, Now that hell has flaſht in your faces, you come in a fit of terror, and you pretend to be ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for your ſins; but let me ſee ſuch things as wil evidence this in after-fruits. Beſide this, they are convinc'd of the truth of the promiſes of God made to his people. And when the terrors which brake in from the threatnings, has made ſome external change upon them, (miſtaking themſelves, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170271:21"/>this which is wrought for a gracious change) they reckon themſelves among the regenerate; and reading the promiſes which are made to theſe, they confidently apply them to themſelves, and that not without abundance of joy. Thus did <hi>Herod, Mark</hi> 6.20. when <hi>Johns</hi> Doctrines had ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions upon him, and theſe had made an alteration in his practiſes and ways, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving reformed many things that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs, now he hears <hi>John</hi> gladly, and he greedily catches at all the ſweet promiſes which <hi>John</hi> dropt at any time to ſuch as did obey the truth, ſaying in his heart Theſe are mine, and this made him hear with delight. Thus the ſtony ground received the word with joy, which muſt needs ariſe from ſome promiſes miſapplyed, and ſome good laid hold on, which did not belong to them, whereby they apprehended that their condition vvas much advanced; they rejoyced in the Heaven and happineſſe which the promiſes held forth to the Saints, (which they could not do unleſſe they had believed them) but they were unwilling to go thorow a believers hell to his Heaven; therefore in time of perſecution they fell away, hence it is that ſome are ſaid to have taſted of the powers of the world to come, <hi>Heb.</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170271:22"/>6.5. that is, they are convinc'd of the excellent priviledges of the Saints, both in this life, and eſpecially in that to come, as that they ſhall have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with <hi>God</hi> the Father, Son, and Spirit, with Angels, and all the Saints. They may be perſwaded of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſtate of the Saints then in reſpect of the glory which ſhall be put upon their ſouls and bodies, their freedome f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om evil, and the acceſſion of all good things. Now though they have not a true taſte of theſe priviledges, and they know not what grace is, and the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of communion with <hi>God</hi> is, yet they being perſwaded that ſuch things are, having found a joy in their falſe hopes, and counterfeit graces which they have judged to be ſoretaſtes of Heaven, they have been ſorc'd to acknowledge that this falſe joy was yet better then all the pleaſures of their ſins, and hence they have been ſtrongly perſwaded of the truth of Gods promiſes made to his people, though they do not belong to them; this is the caſe of many men, who by the perſwaſions of the truth of the threats and promiſes, do not learn
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170271:22"/>to eſcape the one, and to enjoy the other; and they ſay under theſe perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as he did, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.15. <hi>Bleſſed is he that ſhal eat bread in the kingdom of God,</hi> yet themſelves never come there.</p>
               <p>VI. They may be perſwaded of the ſweetneſſe of <hi>Gods</hi> ways, and that thoſe who follow him have their pleaſure, yea more pleaſure then men can have in ſin; it is ſaid therefore they received the word with joy, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.13. and <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 58.2. They delighted in approaching unto <hi>God;</hi> hence it is ſaid, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.5. That they taſted of the good word of <hi>God,</hi> they taſted of the goodneſſe of the word, and having taſted it, they accounted it good. Now we know that the taſte counts nothing good but that vvhich is ſweet, though other ſenſes do count bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things good, for they may be beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, and ſo good to the eye, and fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant, ſo good to the ſmelling, but the palate commends ſweetneſs.</p>
               <p>The carnal man may eſteem the ways of <hi>God</hi> as pleaſant.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170271:23"/>
               <p>Firſt, becauſe the bare performance of ſome duties, and reforming of ſome ſins, bath given much eaſe to conſcience, and hath procured much reſt from the troubles with which they were before overwhelmed: ſo that comparing their lives w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> what they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re before, they do account the much more pleaſant then when they lived in the height of ſin, becauſe they had then many gripings of conſcience which ſpoiled all their mirth; now though they have but a falſe peace, yet it is ſweeter then their former life.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he accounts the ways of God ſweet, becauſe he hath not only a ceſſation from his former troubles, but he hath alſo many times a great preſumption of Gods love, and of the pardon of ſin, and of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life; ſo that he is as it were wrapt up out of the body, and perhaps in a fit out of the world, that he can ſet a low eſteem upon theſe alſo for a time.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, he eſteems the ways of God ſweet, becauſe he finds now an increaſe of knowledge, and of gifts by exerciſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in them: ſo that the knowledge that he gets under the word, makes the word ſeem ſweet unto him, and he rejoyces in it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.35. Knowledge is pleaſant, even of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170271:23"/>that which we do not love; ſo that while this increaſeth the ſoul is delighted, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.2. they delighted in knowing, but not in doing, and as the word may feem ſweet for the knowledge which is gotten by it: ſo may prayer becauſe of gifts and parts increaſed by it; Thus he may be convinced of the ſweetneſs of Gods ways, ſo far that he is carried forth ſometimes to prefer the ways of God before the ways of men, and the people of God before the men of the world, as <hi>Balaam</hi> was, <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.5. <hi>How goodly are thy tents, O Jacob, and thy taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles, O Iſrael!</hi> The Lord is pleaſed to ſhew carnal men that which they never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy; yea they feel ſometimes that which they ſoon forget. They have ſome glances of the happineſs which the Saints enjoy in communion with God, though they have none with him; yet ſome ſuch workings there are ſometimes upon hypocrites, that they finde ſomething which ſeems like it, and brings them in much comfort, which although it be not true and laſting, yet it ſerves to convince them that there is a ſweetneſſe in the ways of God, and they can ſay, Bleſſed is he that is in ſuch a caſe, yea, bleſſed is he whoſe God is the Lord: upon all theſe accounts they are in the main perſwaded there is a ſweetneſs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170271:24"/>in the ways of the Saints, though they do all the while miſtake it, and are ſtrangers to that comfort which the Saints find in duties, when they think they do enjoy them. The ways of God themſelves are not ſweet, but there is a ſweetneſs ſqueezed out of them which refreſhes them, ſo that upon the whole, they are ſatisfied in this, that it is a more comfortable life (all things conſidered) to live in the ſtrict per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances of the godly, then in the looſe practiſes of the wicked; yet theſe men that come thus far, may not be altogether Chriſtians.</p>
               <p n="7">7ly. They may be perſwaded of things that are excellent, and may be able to judg betwixt things that differ, yea ſo far skill'd in the nature of things, that they may be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to inſtruct others in ſpiritual matters: they may have ſome inſight into all the ways of God, in which his people walk; ſo that they may be able to direct the weak, and quicken the dull, yea and to ſet things out with ſome eminency, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Knowing and approving the things that are more excellent, being inſtructed out of the Law.</hi> He may not onely ſee or ſhew what is a du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but the excellency of it, by which he has the advantage of exciting others to it; yea he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ay not only ſhew how much more
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170271:24"/>excellent grace, and the exerciſe of it is then ſin, but if any grace more excellent, or duty then other, he may diſcern the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective and comparative excellency, that is in one more then in another, and yet have no true grace himſelf. Thus vve ſee men in their judgements may be for God in many things, yea in ſo many things, that it is hard to ſhew in what they may not be for him, and yet their wils and affections ſtand at a vaſt diſtance; thus you ſee the judgement may be ſwayed much, and in this reſpect a man may be <hi>almoſt a Chriſtian.</hi> I am now to enquire concerning the Wil, how far that may be inclined; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though every unregenerate perſon is defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive here, and it is the will that lies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind in theſe imperfect perſwaſions; yet the Will is not without ſome motions: he wils ſome things, and does many things, as <hi>Herod</hi> and others did. Let us enquire a little concerning thoſe perſwaſions which reach the wil, yet imperfectly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170271:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>How far the Will may be perſwaded.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt, ſome are ſo far perſwaded to be Chriſtians, that they reſolve to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with all thoſe convictions which <hi>I</hi> ſhewed you they might have, and they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine with themſelves that they will be Chriſtians, though not yet; they ſtick at nothing but the time, they are fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that they muſt be changed; ſuch a ſin muſt be left, and ſuch a duty muſt be taken up. They confeſſe that Repentance and mortiſication of particular corruptions are neceſſary things, and they reſolve with themſelves, that they will practiſe theſe, but they cannot agree upon the time; <hi>I</hi> will do this ſays one, when <hi>I</hi> am old, or vvhen <hi>I</hi> am ſicit, ſays another; then <hi>I</hi> would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly be as ſtrict and holy as the beſt. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers they crave a leſs time; the next year ſays one, <hi>I</hi> wil become a new man; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps another reſolves upon the next moneth, a third craves but a weeks liberty more, a fourth but a day; nay perhaps a man may ſo far comply with his convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that he may! reſolve to do ſomething the next hour, and yet as neer as theſe come
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170271:25"/>up to a complyance with the command of God, they never obey it. See an example of this <hi>Luke</hi> 9.59, 61. One ſays, <hi>I wil but go and bury my Father;</hi> this might have been done in a day, the other ſays, <hi>I wil but go and bid my friends farewel, and then I will come and follow thee,</hi> and this was but an hours work; but Jeſus who ſees not as man ſees, diſcerns the diſtance at which their hearts ſtood from him all this while under this fair perſwaſion; he ſaw that he and they were never like to meet, as near as they ſeemed to be. He knew that theſe would never bid enough for Heaven, as fair as they offered; therefore he preſently falls upon a diſcourſe to ſhew how unfit ſuch merchants were for him, as if he had ſaid to the ſtanders by, You think that <hi>I</hi> have gotten two Diſciples; here are two that wil follow me without diſpute. But you are miſtaken; there is a greater difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them and me then you ſee; this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference about the time is like to part me and them eternally; for if they were fully reſolved to follow me, they would follow me now; theſe delayes and promiſes for to morrow are but a ſmoother kind of deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al then others do give.</p>
               <p>Secondly, ſome are ſo far far perſwaded that they would be Chriſtians, but not in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170271:26"/>all places, they would be Chriſtians in publick, but not in private; they wil go ſo far in profeſſion as others do; they would willingly ſubmit to thoſe things which come under common obſervation; that which is viſible in others, they would willingly have to be manifeſt in them. The form of godlineſs is obvious to all, but the power of godlineſs is a ſecret thing, and conſiſts in ſecret duties which others ſee not, as in cloſet-duties, ſecret Prayer and meditation, and heart-examination; theſe things they wil not touch withall. Such were in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> time, who would have paſt for Gods people in the Congregation, <hi>Eze.</hi> 33.30, 31. they ſat there as Gods people, and they heard the word of the Lord, and they took delight in ſo doing; this they were in publick; but what were they in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate? ſee <hi>Ezek</hi> 8.7, 8, 9. Abominable Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters; thus men wil be Saints in one place, and devils in another; when they come to hear the Word, they would carry a ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance with them; here they will be for Chriſt; but what do they carry of this to their families? there is no ſenſe nor ſavour of thoſe truths which they are affected with under the Ordinance; or if they carry a little of this into their families, and then
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170271:26"/>repeat what they hear, or confer of it with others, yet follow them to their ſecret Chambers, do they carry the impreſſions of truth thither? do they examine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by it there? do they pray over what they hear there where no eye ſees them? ſurely no. Can their private retirements witneſs for them at laſt that they have been ſenſible of their own ſins, and the ſins of others? can the tears dropt there for the ſins of the place ſpeak for them? can their bed-ſides teſtifie for them that they poured out their ſouls by them unto God with ſtrong and daily cries? can the darkneſs of the night bear them record that their me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations have been of God, and that they have been laying of deſigns for the honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of God in their places and ſtations in which God hath ſet them? Oh my friends, conſider theſe things, and examine your ſelves whether you have not been as <hi>Jehu,</hi> zealous for God before men, that you may have even ſaid by your geſture and behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, Come ſee my zeal for the Lord; and yet in private you have minded nothing more then he did, the ſeeking of your ſelves, and the eſtabliſhment of your own houſes; oh when you come into your cloſets, and to your bed-ſides, you ſhould bluſh and be aſhamed to think
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170271:27"/>how much you differ there from your ſelves here. Here you pretend your ſelves to be the ſervants of God, and there you profeſs your ſelves the ſervants of the world; oh how few of thoſe truths have you weighed and conſidered of there, which you have been convinced of here; when you come there, you ſee your books of accounts in one place, your bils of parcels in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your Letters in another: think how much time you have ſpent here in your chaire, and how little upon your knees; here you have been mornings early, and evenings late, but not vvith your Bible be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, nor at prayer or meditation upon ſpiritual matters, but at the affairs of trade. <hi>I</hi> tel you that theſe things will riſe up in judgement againſt you, and condemn you at laſt, and God wil judge you not by what you are before men, but by what you are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in ſecret, for it is this that he moſt obſerves, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.4.6.18: <hi>He ſees in ſecret,</hi> that is, he onely ſees in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, this is his prerogative, for he ſees and regards principally what men do in ſecret; he values more that which men do behind mens backs, then vvhat they do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their faces; he ſees ſo in ſecret, that if men be not the ſame in ſecret that they are in publick, he wil take no notice of it;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170271:27"/>Upon this account he would not know thoſe Formaliſts mentioned <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.16. This vvil be enough to prove you to be but Chriſtians in part, in that you are not Chriſtians in ſecret. <hi>That a man is, that he is when he is alone;</hi> that which a man thinks of, deſignes for, and delights in moſt in private, that ſhews vvhat a man is.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſome are perſwaded to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, but not amongſt all perſons; they will be good amongſt the good, but not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the evil; they can ſwim down the ſtream vvith the godly, but not up the ſtream; like <hi>Peter</hi> they vvil profeſſe vvhile they are amongſt the Diſciples, that they vvil die with Chriſt; but when they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe that deny him, they vvil not know the man. They are not able to ſtand before the breath of a ſcorner; one that ſcoffs at Religion beats them out of their profeſſion. How many be there that vvil profeſſe Chriſt very far amongſt profeſſors, where it is a credit to own God, who yet vvil be aſhamed of this, when they fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe who vvill reproach his vvays? then either they joyn vvith the ſcorner, and deny Chriſt, or elſe ſtand ſtill in a baſe neutrality, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray profeſſion by their ſilence, as if there were a guilt in it. Thus <hi>Saul</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170271:28"/>would be a Prophet amongſt the Prophets, but when he comes into his Family, the evil ſpirit ſeizeth upon him; but ſurely ſuch as theſe will be found too light when they are weighed in the ſcales. Obſerve that of our Saviour, <hi>Mark</hi> 8.38. <hi>Whoſoever ſhal be aſhamed of me, and of my words, in that adulterous and ſinful Generation, of him alſo ſhall the ſon of man be aſhamed, when he cometh in the glory of his father with the bleſſed Angels.</hi> Chriſt wil own thoſe, and thoſe only, who have owned him before wicked men, before ſcoffers and ſcorners, and ſuch as labour to bring ſhame and contempt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all that own God; therefore ſays Chriſt, it is not he that confeſſes me now, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours me ſecretly, or openly before theſe who profeſſe themſelves followers of me and my word that ſhall then be counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanc'd, if he be aſhamed of me before thoſe who labour to make all men aſhamed of me. Oh conſider this you that would be accounted good amongſt them that ſet an high eſteem upon good men: but if you meet with thoſe that ſcoff a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> goodneſs, you are for them too; you are ſilent at leaſt when the ways, and name, and people of God are blaſphemed or reproached, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if it be a friend, or a cuſtomer, or a great man; then you muſt ſay as they ſay,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170271:28"/>or at leaſt ſay nothing to the contrary. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what Chriſt hath ſaid, and how he wil look upon you as being the ſhame of profeſſion, and of his name, when he comes in his glory; how do you expect to be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied before all the world, who dared not to be good in all places, and all companies?</p>
               <p n="4">IV. Some are ſo far perſwaded that they wil be Chriſtians in reſpect of the whole viſibility of profeſſion, but they wil not take up the power and ſpirituality of it; they wil reform ſo far, that they will cleanſe the outſide, abſtain from all viſible ungodlineſs, yea and take the form of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs too, as the Apoſtle mentions ſome who did ſo, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Having a form of godlineſs, and yet they did deny the power;</hi> that is, they did refuſe to ſtoop to the power of it; there are two parts of Religion; the form which is viſible, and lies open to men; this conſiſts in reforming the outward man, the denying of ungodlineſs and worldly luſts; this is the negative part. It lies alſo in a performance of all thoſe duties which come under the obſervation of others, as hearing the Word, reading, conferring of it, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the publick, and in our families, with a ſober and unblameable conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation towards men. All this a man
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170271:29"/>may ſubmit unto, and yet be but almoſt a Chriſtian. For there is yet another part of Religion which is the very ſoul of it; and this lies hid from the eyes of others, and conſiſts in two things principally. Firſt, in the performance of ſecret duties, as ſelf-denial, ſelf-tryal and examination, watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs over their hearts and thoughts, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying of inward corruptions. Secondly, it conſiſteth in the frame and bent of the heart, in theſe and all other duties towards God. The main of Religion lies here in fearing and loving of God. Theſe are things which men may, and do often omit and paſſe over, who yet do embrace the whole body and outſide of Godlineſſe. Praying, Reading, Hearing are but the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet which contain this Jewel. But god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs conſiſteth in a right and true diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the heart under theſe. Now if Chriſtianity did imply no more then moſt men conceive it doth, if it were only an abſtaining from groſs and common pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the world, and taking up of all thoſe duties which are commonly confeſt to be ſuch, by men profeſſing themſelves Chriſtians, they would be Chriſtians alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. But the Lord will finde amongſt thoſe that perform the duties which make men viſible Chriſtians, and ſubmit to all
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170271:29"/>his Ordinances, many that are but almoſt Chriſtians at the moſt, and that upon this account, becauſe they never attended unto the ſpirituality of duties. They prayed and heard the word, &amp; received the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but they were carnal ſtill; their old hearts did continue; their practices were changed, but their principles and their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts were the ſame ſtill; their faces were turned but not their affections; the one ſtood towards God, but the other was toward ſome luſt or other.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Some would be Chriſtians in all things, till it come to the beloved ſin, till it come to profit and loſſe, and when they are touched here, they cry out, The Lord pardon me in this one thing. If the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter preſs at any time upon men the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of an univerſal change, they miſtake it, and think that by this univerſal we mean a general change, that is, a change in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter] and more viſible part; A leaving the greater number of known ſins, and a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to the greater number of known du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; they think no rule ſo general, but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of ſome exceptions in particulars. They think one ſin may be reſerved with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice to their cloſing with Chriſt, and think they may hold faſt enough with one hand upon him, though they keep the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170271:30"/>other to take hold of ſin and vanity. If at any time they apprehend the truth as bent againſt the toleration of any ſin, and they ſee a neceſſity of parting with <hi>Dalilah,</hi> or Heaven, then they ſay This is a hard ſaying, who can hear it? They would willingly be followers of Chriſt, if he would give them a diſpenſation for ſome things which they account but ſmal: though the leaſt ſin is too bigg to lie with Chriſt in the heart. How many do part with Chriſt upon this point, when he comes to croſs their profit and gain, who yet are troubled to loſe him, and go away like the young man, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.22. with tears in their eyes! they will do much rather then live without hopes of Heaven, til it come to the cutting off the right hand or foot, or plucking out of the right eye; this is like the way in which <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> parted. Chriſt and they go together in many things, but when they come here they muſt needs part.</p>
               <p n="6">VI. Some are ſo far perſwaded to be Chriſtians, that they are aſhamed to be reckoned amongſt the oppoſers of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. They abhor the ſeat of the ſcorner, and wil not willingly hear godlineſs deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; they are convinc'd of the happineſſe of thoſe that fear God, and are convinc'd who they are, they would willingly be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170271:30"/>favourers of ſuch, and wiſh they were in their conditions: yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all theſe things, ſomething holds them from coming up fully to their ſteps; either they are poſſeſt with a ſluggiſh ſpirit, and wil not ſet themſelves forth in the duties of a Chriſtian, or elſe they are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly glued to the world, and wil not run the hazards of Chriſtians. One plays the ſluggard under his convictions, and cries out thus, I would fain have knowledg, but I cannot allow the time to ſearch the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, nor to read good Books, nor to fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent the company and conferences of the people of God; another ſays, I approve of Prayer, it is a duty, but <hi>I</hi> have not parts nor praying gifts; theſe are but idle excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of hearts that will not come up to God fully; for were your hearts ſet to know God, you would find time enough out of your idle and unneceſſary buſineſſes to ſeek after knowledg, nay you would cut it out of your time that you ſpend in eating, drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and ſleeping; have you not borrowed ſometime from theſe to ſatisfie your luſts? and for you who pretend an excuſe for the omitting and neglecting of duties in your Families, and in private, which you are convinc'd ought to be done,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170271:31"/>and you think to ſalve it with this that you have no parts; alas this is a fiction in ſome, and a vain excuſe in all that plead it.</p>
               <p>For 1. Have you not abilities to expreſs your preſent apprehenſions, and concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to all men you meet with all, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with? are you not able to ſpeak appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitely and readily in buying and ſelling? you that can expreſs what you conceive of all matters that come before you, may conclude that neglect of prayer does not ariſe from a defect of expreſſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If God ſhould take you, and ſhake you over hell, and you had but eminent and deep impreſſions of your danger herein, you would ſurely then pray and cry; you would finde words if you did feel your wants, or apprehend your danger; it is nothing that you want but impreſſion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Do you not ſee men abundantly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath you in parts add natural abilities, that yet are able to come to God with boldneſs, ſpeak out their own and others wants free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God?</p>
               <p n="4">4. <q>Know, it is not parts but grace that fits a man for duty. I never knew any that were wrought upon truly, how ever weak in parts, but was able to Pray without a Book; and <hi>I</hi> do believe that the ſpirit of Prayer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s an eſſential part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the work
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170271:31"/>of grace, <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15. And that a man may as well live without breath, as he can be a Chriſtian with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſpirit of prayer.</q>
               </p>
               <p n="5">V. Be thy parts never ſo low &amp; weak, yet uſe them for God, &amp; he will augment them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.29. <hi>To him that hath ſhall be given.</hi> Grace wil bring with it ſuch gifts as are of abſolute neceſſity to maintain a communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with God, and ſuch is the ſpirit of Prayer: never any man did conſcientiouſly uſe weak and tender parts for God, but like the bread which Chriſt brake for the multitude, they did increaſe upon his hands in breaking.</p>
               <p>Beſides theſe which are hindered by a ſlothful ſluggiſh ſpirit, others come not up fully to the life of Chriſtians, from a ſecret tie which is betwixt them and the world; they are loth to hazard their peace or cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit amongſt men. Many men notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding they are convinc'd of the ways of God, and how they ought to walk, yet are ſo ſtudious of a peaceable quiet being in the world, and ſo covetous of every ones good word, that they had rather venture the loſs of Heaven, then the diſpleaſing of any man; they wil be for godlineſs in their opinion, and they wil own the people of God, until it comes to this, that they muſt
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170271:32"/>appear, they muſt ſhew themſelves, and this wil diſpleaſe ſuch a friend, and ſuch a neighbour, and they ſhal ſuffer by being counted a man of this or that partie; this makes them draw in, as the Phariſes did, who believed, but yet would not profeſſe Chriſt; they would ſhew any under-hand kindneſſe to him, but they would not be openly ſeen to be his followers, eſpecially where their peace or credit would be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, <hi>John</hi> 12.42. <hi>Nevertheleſſe, among the chief Rulers alſo many beleeved on him, but becauſe of the Phariſees, they did not confeſſe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, leſt they ſhould be put out of the ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue:</hi> Thus you ſee many men go far, not onely in reſpect of conviction, but alſo of complyance with the truth and ways of God, and they ſeem to moſt men to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together Chriſtians, and to the beſt of men to be almoſt ſuch, and yet they are as far from being that which they would be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, and what others deſire they would be, as <hi>Agrippa</hi> here was from being a Chriſtian, who was never ſuch. Thus I have finiſhed the firſt head, and have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en you what kind of perſwaſions theſe are which are found in ſuch as are termed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>The next thing which was propoſed to be opened, is the ſpring and riſe of theſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170271:32"/>perſwaſions; in which I am to conſider,</p>
               <p>Firſt, the extent of theſe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the defects of them; and here I am to ſhew you whence it is that carnal men are ſo far perſwaded, that they ſeem to be almoſt Chriſtians, and then bow it comes to paſs, that being brought ſo far, they do not prove altogether Chriſtians.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Whence theſe perſwaſions do ariſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen we conſider the thick darkneſs that is in the underſtanding natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and that groſs oppoſition and enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that is in the wil againſt God, and his ways, we may juſtly wonder how it comes to paſs, that any truth gets into the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and that it ſhould find any kinde of complyance or favourable entertainment in the latter; yet conſulting with experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, we may ſee that the truth doth get in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the underſtanding by way of conviction, and into the wil by way of perſwaſion, and works to a very great height both ways in thoſe who yet do not graciouſly ſubmit un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and obey it from the heart, and if we lay our reaſon to our experience, we may p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rceive that this ariſeth</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:170271:33"/>
               <p n="1">1. From the relicks of the light that are found in the natural conſcience, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.27. <hi>The underſtanding of a man is the candle of the Lord.</hi> The Lord ſet up a light that ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed gloriouſly in the ſoul at firſt, and caſt her beams far and near, ſo that it was able to ſee a far off: and all the off-ſprings of his reaſon, even down to a thouſand Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, were yet pure, and ful of light; ſo that although man had made a thouſand inferences from one principle, the laſt had been as ful of light and clearneſs as the firſt. The ſoul has now loſt that vigour and ſtrength to diſcern things remote; yet ſhe is not wholly without light, but as a candle ſhews thoſe things which are neer it very plainly, though ſuch as are remote, it diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers weakly or not at all: ſo that light which was once in man, and did like the ſun ſend forth his beams to the remoteſt parts of the horizon, now being weak and languiſhing, diſcovers onely ſome few things. The ſoul dos ſtil retain ſome of its firſt-born notions, wch do ſhine forth in pure and unſpotted beams, ful of convincing light, and of undoubted truth, in which all agree. Jew, and Gentile, Barbarian and Scythian, bond and free; theſe are the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon principles vvhich boil up in every man, and do riſe with that ſtrength and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170271:33"/>clearneſs that none can fully ſtop them who have induſtriouſly endeavoured it.</p>
               <p>Such as theſe:</p>
               <p>Firſt, that there is a God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that the ſoul is immortal.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that there is a Law by which man ought to ſtear all his actions; and as they do agree or diſagree with this, ſo they are to be accounted good or evil.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that this God who gives Laws to all creatures, eſpecially to man is juſt, and wil in Juſtice puniſh thoſe who wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly break his Laws; Theſe are truths which we may find in the conſciences of all men that have no light, but that of nature, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.32. <hi>Who knowing the judgement of God, (that they which commit ſuch things are worthy of death) not onely do the ſame, but have pleaſure in them that do them, Rom.</hi> 2.14, 15. <hi>When the Gentiles which have not the law do by nature the things contained in the law: theſe having not the law, are a law unto themſelves, which ſhew the work of the law written in their hearts, their conſcience alſo bearing witneſſe, and their thoughts the mean while accuſing or elſe excuſing one another:</hi> Nay if the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaid nothing of the complyance of the Heathen with them, they themſelves would abundantly teſtifie their agreement with the Scriptures in theſe things. I might raiſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170271:34"/>all the Philoſophers out of their graves to hiſs the Atheiſts of this Age out of the world, who would deny thoſe to be men that denyed a God, and would reckon thoſe as beaſts, and worſe, that would queſtion the immortality of the ſoul, or queſtion whether the creature ſhould receive a law from his Creator, or that ſhould claim to themſelves a liberty to do what they liſt, as if there were no ſtandard to meaſure good and evil by. The Heathen would make many practical Atheiſts to bluſh at laſt, who could ſay, <hi>Non ſolum jus &amp; injuria a natura dijudicantur, ſed omnia omnino honest a &amp; tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia; nam &amp; communis intelligentia nobis res notas efficit, ea quaein animis noſtris inchoavit, ut honeſta in virtute ponantur, in vitiis turpia.</hi> We are not only able (ſays he) to judg of right and wrong betwixt man and man; but we are able to diſcern what is good, and what is evil, and all this by the light of nature. God has made ſuch indelible ſtamps and impreſſions of theſe firſt principles upon mans reaſon, that til he be extreamly cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, or Judicarily hardened, he diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers a tranſcending excellency in goodneſs, and an infamous blot upon wickedneſs; yea they who for the love of ſin (that they might enjoy it quietly,) have laboured to ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence theſe firſt whiſperings of nature, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170271:34"/>to blot out what the finger of God hath written upon their hearts, have but labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to waſh the Blackamore white; &amp; when the Atheiſt in practiſe has laboured to be ſo in opinion, he has been but a Sceptick at laſt; theſe truths like nature under forcé return upon them again, and they are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times conſtrained to fear the Deity that they flout at, and to dread him that they have oft denied. Now ſeeing it is thus, that ſuch ſeeds of the knowledg of good and evil are left in every mans heart natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, it may wel be, and does very oft fall out, that when men come under the word (before they have ſinned away this light, and are brought to a deadly Palſie) by that oil which the ordinances do add to this lamp, and by acceſſion of more light from the ſame, men ſee theſe things more clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and many things more which were too remote to be diſcovered by their firſt light; hence it comes to paſs that he that by the light of nature ſaw that there was a God, now ſees ſomething of the nature of God, of his worſhip, and is inſtructed in this; he that ſaw that the ſoul was immortal, and that there vvas a bleſſedneſs or miſery fitted to it, ſees vvhere &amp; what it is. He that ſaw ſin confuſedly, novv ſees it more diſtinctly; yea he ſees not only theſe things, but deduceth
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170271:35"/>many things from theſe, and may have a general inſight into all the ways of God, ſo that men meerly inlightned, and having their naturals poliſhed and varniſhed over by the often rubbing over of the Word, may come to great convictions of the truths of God. yea, and theſe convictions may have ſome con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>derable influence upon their wils without the help of grace, by the help of this one thing, which is the nature of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very being, it loves and ſeeks his own good; this is the language of every being, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Who will ſhew us any good.</hi> No man ſeeks evil formally as ſuch, but as it is diſguized by Satan, or dreſt up by his own wanton and corrupt fancy, and made to appear in the habit of goodneſs, as the Witch of <hi>Endor</hi> raiſed up the devil in <hi>Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muels</hi> garments. Thus as men are convinc'd of the good that is in God, and his ſervice, ſo they may from thoſe common convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſet themſelves to ſeek him, and apply themſelves to his ways and ordinances. And though no man ſees the chief good in God and his ways, but he that is graciouſly inlightened; yet common light may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover a kind of good in God, and in the ſeeking of him; and proportionable to the good they diſcover in ſpiritual things are their perſwaſions to embrace, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170271:35"/>to attain them. Hence many without grace go far, but none far enough to reach the kingdom of God; we have an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of this in the young man, <hi>Matthew</hi> 19.20. who without ſpecial grace upon the ſtock of his natural abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, with the additional light of the means under which he lived, went very far in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Law, and offered very fair at Heaven, ſeeing doubtleſs a great good in ſalvation; but the reaſon why he went not through with his purchaſe was this, he ſaw not the ſupream good in it; though he apprehended it a good thing to inherite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life, yet he ſaw ſomething which to him was better; had this been the chief good in his account, it would have been his chief deſire. And doubtleſs ſeeing all have the ſame ſtock of theſe firſt principles to trade upon, by living under the meanes they may be ſo heightned, that they may ſee (what he did) a degree of goodneſs and happineſs in the enjoyment of ſpiritual things, and may be induced to do, even as he did (having a proportionable meaſure of perſwaſion) to embrace thoſe things, and to comply with the means leading to them. Theſe are perſwaſions, or elſe they would not be moved to do any thing; they are not ful perſwaſions, for then they
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170271:36"/>would ſtick at nothing: but they are imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, &amp; are more or leſs, according to thoſe apprehenſions which they have of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of God, and of his ways, of which the natural man by the light of nature, and the ſuper-added light of the word, may have a weak ſight, but without the work of grace cannot have a true ſight, ſuch as ſhould draw him out to ſeek after <hi>God</hi> with all his heart; yet though he ſees not all, he ſees much; and though he will not do all that he is commanded, yet he wil be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to do many things; for though a carnal man cannot apprehend any good in the ſtricteſt profeſſion of godlineſs, which is accompanied with the greateſt ſelf, deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and expoſes men to the greateſt hazards, yet he dos oft apprehend much good in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial complyance with Religion; for this he ſuppoſes may not ſpoil his particular inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and yet may attain the end, which is true happineſs; upon this account moſt men have their meaſures of perſwaſion, ſome are greater, &amp; ſome leſs, but ſome do border upon a ful perſwaſion, they are almoſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, or perſwaded to be <hi>almoſt Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 Theſe perſwaſions do ariſe from good education in many, good counſel &amp; inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions being wrought wiſely into them by the skil and induſtry of their Parents and friends; &amp; theſe being backt with good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, &amp; fenced by diſcipline, many have
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170271:36"/>been drawn by love to entreat, or driven by fear into a profeſſion of what is good, &amp; by long cuſtom they ſeem to have gotten a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and they act in a profeſſion as if they were diſpoſed to it by grace; &amp; whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es they want the temptations which others have, they ſeem to be fully perſwaded to be <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians;</hi> but when friends or parents are taken away, who were as a hedg about them, and kept many temptations from approaching neer them; or when they are taken from their friends, and called to live upon their own ſtock in ſome place, where they ſee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther examples, &amp; meet with temptations of all ſorts, they ſoon ſhew what, and whence their former perſwaſions were: they ſhew that ignorance of evil, or want of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to it only made them ſeem good; But without doubt next unto grace, good edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation dos moſt of all work upon the ſpirits of men, yea it can do any thing but renew the heart: we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee how children ſuck in the opinions and perſwaſions of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and ordinarily they do more zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly defend what came from them by tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition then what the light of the word af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded them. Nay it is no very difficult thing for parents to draw their children to imitate the; for the examples of thoſe whom vve love, perſwade to that which for itſelf we do not love, yea and being drawn once to do any thing in imitation of anot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170271:37"/>whom we honour, we continue in it, leſt we ſhould be a diſhonour to our copie; and thus by continuance we come to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of what we do, and ariſe ſo high in notion and external profeſſion, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is wanting but the power of thoſe truths which we aſſent unto, and ſpirituali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of thoſe duties which we perform. Thus the Parent or the maſter makes his child or ſervant almoſt a Chriſtian; but its the Lord only can make him altogether ſuch.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Convictions and perſwaſions riſe high by ſome ſpecial providence; God knocks ſo hard at the door of natural mens conſciences by ſome afflictions, or emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent danger of death, that although he does not open the heart as he did <hi>Lydias,</hi> yet he makes a breach, at which ſome truth enters, which coming in with ſuch conviction and power, for the preſent (yea and perhaps for the future) makes ſome changes in the mans apprehenſions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions. Thus <hi>Pharoah</hi> himſelf was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of the power of God under affliction, whom he would not know in proſperity. When Gods providences were calm, he thunders, as if there were none greater then he; but when God thunders, he is calm, and is brought by degrees as the ſtorm did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, to conſent to <hi>Moſes</hi> demands, though
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170271:37"/>never fully and with all his heart. <hi>Ahab</hi> when he was terrified with the ſharp meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> how does he ſeem as a man changed, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.27. he puts aſhes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his head, girds him with ſackcloth, as a man mortified and dead to this world; yet who that reads the ſtory of <hi>Ahabs</hi> life, judges this to be any more, then the light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which ſhined in his conſcience while the Prophet thundred. Thus we ſee men upon a ſick-bed, while they are under ſtrong apprehenſions and fears of death, yea and of hel too, promiſe much to others, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve much with themſelves, yea and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade themſelves that they are in good earneſt, and engage if God ſpare them, that they wil be altogether Chriſtians, and give great hopes to others, while the leaſt we can judge of them is, that they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Chriſtians. There is no evil that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience convinceth them of, or any friend can mind them of in their former lives, but they wil confeſs, lament, and covenant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt; no duty then diſcovered, but they wil aſſent unto, and ngage to take up if God wil try them, the terrors of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty are ſo dreadful, that they vvil do any thing rarher then go to hell. Thus <hi>Francis Spira,</hi> who deliberately and in cold blood denyed the truth, yet when he lay in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170271:38"/>his bitter agonies, he ſaid, if he might be but freed from them, he vvould deſpiſe all the tyrants in the vvorld, he vvould never be afraid to profeſs the truth vvith the greateſt hazard. When the fooliſh Virgins were alarumed with the noiſe of that dreadful cry at midnight, <hi>Behold the Bridegroom comes,</hi> they then begin to look to their Lamps, and they begin to cry for oyl, a thing vvhich they never ſought for before; when they vvere awakened vvith the terror of the Lords approach, then they run too and fro from one to another, crying, give me a little of your oyl; nothing leſs enquired for before, nothing askt for elſe now, though it be a truth, that the Judge ſtands before the door, <hi>James</hi> 5.9. yet men are nothing moved at this, they wil lie ſtil as long as he ſtands ſtil; but when he begins to knock at the door by ſome ſpecial pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and threatens to come in ſpeedily, then you ſhall ſee how a man wil beſtir himſelf, he vvil do any thing, ſuffer any thing rather then <hi>God</hi> ſhould break in upon him in this condition; then for a meſſenger, for a Miniſter, or ſome underſtanding Chriſtian to inſtruct him, ot intercede for him; there can be nothing then propoſed to him while the dread of the Almighty is upon him, that he wil not ſubmit unto, and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170271:38"/>accept of; and all this while the heart may not be changed; all this may ariſe from hence, he begins to ſee what a fearful thing it is to fal into the hands of the living <hi>God;</hi> thus the Lord who ſtands always at the door, knocks at mens conſciences at one time or other; at ſome mens often, and ſome ſtronger as wel as oftener; and it is no wonder if ſuch ſtroaks do beat in ſome light into the ſoul, and make ſome change in a mans reſolutions for preſent, and practice afterward.</p>
               <p n="4">4. From the ſearching and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing power of the Word under which men live. The Word is ſharper then a two edg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſword, a diſcerner of the heart and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret thoughts; it enters into the very ſouls of the wicked, and diſcovers what is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, but doth not change them; it works a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, though not a regeneration, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12. <hi>The word of God is quick and powerful, ſharper then any two-edged ſword, piercing even to the dividing aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the ſoul and ſpirit, and of the joynts and marrow, and is a diſcerner of the thoughts, and intents of the heart.</hi> Thus the wicked themſelves have found. How did <hi>Paul</hi> get into <hi>Faelix</hi> his conſcience, and ranſaked it? what an Earth-quake vvas there for
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170271:39"/>the preſent? The Judge on the Bench trembles, while the priſoner at the Bar preaches. This is the caſe of many a ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer at godlineſs, and of ſuch as deride and deſpiſe the Preachers and profeſſors of it; they come to hear for novelty, as <hi>Faelix</hi> would hear <hi>Paul;</hi> but the Miniſter (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the contemptible thoughts they have of him, and the reſolutions they have to ſleight all that he ſays) gets within them, rips up their hearts, ſhews them the ſecrets of their thoughts, and they are ſo far awed with this, that they go away con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of the evil of their thoughts and wayes, and perhaps reſolved to be other men; yet time and temptation eat out theſe things, becauſe there is no depth of earth for theſe to take rooting in.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Men go thus far to quiet their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; though an unregenerate man will do nothing for God, yet he wil do much for his peace; when once the word hath a wakened conſcience, and rowſed that, when it hath taken him by the throat, and brought him to the judgement, then he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently cries for compoſition, then he deſires a parley, and then he makes termes for his peace; Any thing to ſtop the mouth of an accuſing conſcience, eſpecially if it begin to condemn, as wel as to accuſe. Hence it
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170271:39"/>is, that many wicked men do many things in which they neither pleaſe <hi>God,</hi> nor <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves;</hi> they <hi>pleaſe not God,</hi> becauſe they do them not upon good principles; they <hi>pleaſe not themſelves</hi> becauſe they are contrary to their luſts, which yet are as ſtrong in them as ever; but they do them to calm conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; they think it better to liſten to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience rather then to their corruptions, becauſe the pleaſure of ſin doth not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervail the ſorrow and trouble that it brings with it; and ſurely this is the ſtrength of ſuch mens reformation, their preſent peace is broken, conſcience is enlightned, they muſt either deny their luſts, or live in a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent hel; if it were not for this preſent fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſte of evil, they would not be moved, they would deſpiſe all the evil which is threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to come.</p>
               <p n="6">6. God hath ſome ſpecial ends in theſe things: as</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>God</hi> hath a deſign to honour the word, and he makes the wicked themſelves witneſſes of the truth, and power of it, as wel as the godly. They carry up and down in their lives the pledges of the ſame. For their reſtraints do prove the power of it as wel as the others converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Though they wil not love <hi>God</hi> and his ways, yet <hi>God</hi> wil make them fear, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170271:40"/>though we do not preach to their hearts, yet we ſhall preach to their conſciences: and they ſhal be brought in at the laſt to prove what we preached was true, they themſelves having experienced it. Nay let me add this, that the bridling and curbing of wicked men by the Word is a greater evidence (in ſome ſenſe of the power of it) then the governing of the godly. Thoſe few things which the wicked do for fear of the Word, ſhews the power of God more then thoſe many things which the Saints do for love of it; the reaſon is this, becauſe the godly have new and tender hearts, which are eaſily wrought upon, and are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to comply with every command of God; but the other have hard and ſtony hearts, unapt to yeild. The ſtrength or ſharpneſs of a ſword is more ſeen by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a ſmal impreſſion upon ſteel or ſtone, then a large one upon wax; and ſurely Gods word is glorified not onely by converting, but by reſtraining; by chaining up the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as wel as leading the Lamb; the ſcars which unregenerate men carry of the Miniſtry, prove it mighty through God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Gods end is to give men here a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſte of the judgement to come; God keeps <q>a petty ſeſſions here, before the great Aſſiſe. <hi>Faelix</hi> had a taſte of this Judgement;</q> the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170271:40"/>Lord made him to feel ſomething of what he heard, and while <hi>Paul</hi> was reaſoning of judgement ro come, <hi>God</hi> made it ſeem pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and the Judge is by the authority of the Word put into the place of the priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; he trembles as if he were really at the Bar, which <hi>Paul</hi> had but now diſcovered, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.25. Thus the Lord deals often with wicked men, who ſleight all bonds, and caſt the cords of <hi>God</hi> far from them; he binds them faſt in irons, and reſerves them in chains for judgement to come; and though they ſeem to have the only liberty of all men, and to enjoy all pleaſure, yet they carry ſome reliſhes of this day upon their ſpirits, which are as the chains which the priſoner draggs after him. Nay he dos not only keep them in irons thus, but he gives them ſome taſts of hel it ſelf, ſuch as <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> had, and then he takes them out of one hel, and throws them into another, as the Saints are in Heaven, oft times before they die, in the aſſurance of their intereſt in it: ſo wicked men are oft in hel before-hand, by their fore-taſt of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To leave men inexcuſable; nothing wil ſtrip them ſo naked at the laſt day as theſe perſwaſions which they had; according to the meaſure and clearneſs of theſe, ſuch
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170271:41"/>wil be their ſhame, and ſuch will be their confuſion, to ſee how near they came to the kingdom of <hi>God,</hi> and yet ſhut out. <hi>God</hi> convin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es thoſe of ſin whom he intends to ſave, that they may condemn themſelves, and juſtifie <hi>God</hi> here; and he convinces ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whom be intends not to ſave, that they may be forced to juſtifie him hereafter, when he ſhal condemn them, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 51.3, 4. <hi>Againſt thee have I ſinned, that thou mayeſt be juſtified when thou ſpeakeſt, and pure when thou judgeſt. David</hi> did not ſin that God might be juſtified, but <hi>David</hi> was convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of his ſin, that <hi>God</hi> might be cleared, and <hi>David</hi> condemned in himſelf. Saints convictions make them humble themſelves, and the convictions &amp; reſtraints which are thereby made upon wicked men, will make very much for the juſtifying of <hi>God</hi> at the laſt, and for the taking of all excuſe from them; for they can never anſwer this plea: If there were not evil in ſin, why did you fear or refrain from any? and if there was evil in it, why did you not refrain all ſin? and this will ſtop their mouths, that they had knowledg of this day, &amp; of the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it; for <hi>God</hi> wil take out a copy of the Judgement of the day out of their own conſciences.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170271:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Shewing the reaſons why men ſo far perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded go no further.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</hi> How comes it to paſs that men thus far perſwaded go no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
               <p>As it is a wonder that men go ſo far as ſome do without grace; ſo it is as ſtrange a thing, that being brought ſo far, they ſhould ſtop here; but this is</p>
               <p>Firſt, from Satan; he labours to blinde their eyes, that they ſhould not ſee the things that belong to their peace; but if he cannot keep them in a groſs darkneſs, and in a total neglect of Heaven, then he hath a hundred ways to couzen them, and to bring them to compoſition, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them to half it with God; if he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not keep them where they are, yet he will make them ſit down in the mid way to Heaven; he knows that he that underbids ſhal buy the truth no more then he that never cheapens it. He knows Chriſt hath ſet the price upon it, and he that vvil not give all that he hath for the kingdome of Heaven, ſhal as ſurely loſe it, as he that wil give nothing. He that wil keep one ſin,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170271:42"/>or deny one command of Chriſt to ſubmitt to it, ſhall thereby be excluded as well as he that yeelds in nothing to Chriſt; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill does labour therefore to hinder awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened ſoules from comming up fully to Chriſt; when he cannot hinder them from doing ſomething, he wil perſwade them to keep the right hand, or to ſpare the right eye. If they will take their lamps, yet he wil not ſuffer them to take oyl for their veſſells; and this way Satan couſins not a few, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be tempted to ſitt ſtill, yet are eaſily kept from preſſing forward to the mark.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rea.</hi> 2 From their conſciences. Conſcience having attained its end which was peace, the man ſits down. It was nothing, but trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of conſcience at firſt that makes ſuch men ſtirr, and now, by doing ſomething, having obtained a little peace, they ſay, ſoul, thou haſt enough; they never act in religion beyond neceſſitie; nor goe further then the terrours and feares of conſcience will drive them; and theſe are oft times removed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out grace, and they ſit down without Chriſt. I ſhewed you in the former how the devill did hide from them the extent of their duties, and the latitude of Chriſt commands, that ſo they might not attempt to goe far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> might conſent unto, with
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170271:42"/>ſecurity to his own intereſt in them, having cozened them into a good opinion of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves &amp; miſ-repreſented the work of grace, and the change which is wrought in them; they think all is wel, and conſcience is in a great calme, and this being once aſleepe againe they ſettle upon their lees; the dregs which are yet left are not purged out; for all the motions of man which proceed from no other principle then the feares of death &amp; hel, carry a man no farther then to ſeeke his own peace; the conſcience is wounded, and if the man can lick that whole again, hee is quiet; but if the will were wrought upon he would not ſet down till he were perfectly changed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 3. may be from their own corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Being awakned by the word they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſtirr under the ſenſe of the danger, and being convinced of the truth they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it with joy, and like <hi>Herod</hi> do many things, til it comes to ſome peculiar corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and there they are ſtopped; there is ſome darling luſt or other that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not leap over; they march like <hi>Jehu</hi> furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly vvith a ſeeming zeal for God, til they come to the golden Calves of <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> and they cannot pull theſe down; ſome luſt, ſome intereſt, ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage hinders them from following
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170271:43"/>of Chriſt fully, and had they but grace in their wils ſutable to the light in their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, they would be Chriſtians in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as in the caſe of <hi>Jehu,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 10.25, 29, 30. The young man in the goſpel goes on very chearfully, and bids fair for Heaven, as one that was reſolved to have it upon any termes, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.20. <hi>What lack I yet?</hi> He ſeems to be vvilling to give more for Heaven, then all had yet given, and to do more, then yet he had done, as if all that God had required in the law had been too little, and too low a price for glory; but when Chriſt makes a propoſal to him which met with his darling ſin, which was the love of the world, he goes away ſorrowful. This man that was ſo near the kingdome of Heaven in all appearance, leaves it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him for the love of one corruption; this is the caſe of every haif-Chriſtian; one Iuſt or other hinders them, (though they ſeem to run wel) and parts Chriſt and them for ever.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 4. From the meanes they live under; they may live under a fawning and flattering Miniſtry, who vvil perſwade them that the ſmoak is a fire, and the ſpark is a flame, that cry peace, peace where there is none, healing their vvounds ſleightly, and daubing them vvith untempered mortar,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170271:43"/>
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.10. How many are there that go to Hel in peace, whom their Miniſters ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonize here for Saints? how many are care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs of themſelves, by reaſon of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters conſidence, who wil ſalute his people by the name of beleevers, as if he knew their place in Heaven? This makes them think they live high, when indeed 'tis he that preaches low, and that all is wel, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he never ſhewed them how ill it is. Men preach the work of converſion by halves, they ſearch not their people to the quick, they come not neer the conſciences of their hearers, neither do they labour to do it; if they can cloath their matter in ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and ſoft language that may pleaſe the ears of their people, and gaine applauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, they think all is wel; and it is no vvonder if they think as they do, and thus both go down ſlumbering into hel.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 5. May be in reſpect of God, and that in a four-fold account.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In reſpect of his Juſtice, he puniſhes their diſobedience to their former light, by vvith-holding of light from them, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.28. and becauſe when they had but little they were not faithful with that, therefore God wil truſt them but with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; it is juſt vvith God to puniſh the abuſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170271:44"/>of natural light and gifts, by a with-hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſupernatural.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God doth it to ſhew his ſoveraignty; grace is abſolutery his own; he ows it no man, but gives it to whom he pleaſeth; he denies it to the inlightned and convinced, and to him that is almoſt a Chriſtian, he refuſeth to the Scribes and Phariſees, and gives it to Publicans and harlots, <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.31. that men might know that he wil do what pleaſeth him with his own.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That he might ſhew what the will of man is, and how vain a thing when left to it ſelf. God wil have us to ſee that it is not of him that willeth, or of him that runneth, but of God which ſheweth mercy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.16. If it lay in the wil of man, doubtleſs men ſo far perſwaded would turn to God.</p>
               <p n="4">4 God orders it ſo, that he might be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10. in them that beleeve, that they that are ſaved may ſee its wholly from God, when the people of God ſhal ſee thoſe that followed them ſo cloſe in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, that they tread upon their heels, and perhaps in parts and common gifts exceeded them, when they ſhal ſee theſe ſtanding on the left hand, and themſelves on the right, they wil then eaſily ſee what it was that made them to differ,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170271:44"/>they wil then cry out, grace, grace, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the wiſdom of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP, VII. <hi>The firſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of the Doctrine.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>USE</hi> 1. This ſpeaks terror to thoſe that are not at all perſwaded to be chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. If thoſe that are almoſt chriſtians are like to fal ſhort, what wil become of thoſe who are ſo far from being chriſtians, that they have onely the name, and nothing elſe? that have not the ſhew and appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of being ſuch? what wil become of the prophane, the Drunkard, the Swearer, the Scoffer, the Sabbath-breaker, and the unclean, of him that is ſo far from carrying oyl in his veſſel, that he hath none in his lamp? if thoſe that in the judgement of many paſſe for righteous, ſhal miſcarry, what wil become of thoſe whom all men brand with the name of wicked &amp; ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? If ſome ſhal be ſent to hel from the ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of the Saints, who went ſo far, that they were not diſcerned by the ſtricteſt profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, as the fooliſh Virgins: what wil become
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170271:45"/>of them, that are the companions of the wicked, that eat and drink with the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. If God deal thus with the green tree that hath leaves, yea and ſome fruit, becauſe his fruit is ſowre, or not ripe: what wil the Lord do with the tree that is dryed up, and hath neither fruit nor yet leaves? ſurely <hi>God</hi> wil bind theſe up in bundles, and caſt them into everlaſting burnings. O conſider with your ſelves, you have heard how far a man may go, and yet be but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt a Chriſtian; are not many of you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd that you fal ſhort of theſe, and that you come not neer thoſe vvho yet ſal ſhort of the mark of the high calling? if theſe ſhal periſh vvho go beyond you; hovv can you poſſibly eſcape that come not up to them? ſurely this muſt needs convince many of you, that your coudition is ful of palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and manifeſt danger; Ile not ſpend time to reaſon out the miſery of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, nor to convince you concerning theſe things, for you carry up and down with youthe vvorm vvhich gnaws you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. The Drunkard and the Swearer I am perſwaded, is condemned of himſelf; but <hi>I</hi> ſhal haſten to addreſs my ſelf to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſort of people vvho are ready to be more quiet then you, and to pleaſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in hopes that it is not ſo bad vvith
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170271:45"/>them as vvith others, vvhen perhaps it is vvorſe with them then all the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> ſhal now turn my ſelf towards thoſe who would be accounted Chriſtians, and do in a meaſure and degree more or leſs comply with the ways of <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>The Second <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe which is of Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>USE</hi> 2. Give me leave (my friends) to make application of all that hah been ſaid unto you, for I have ſpoken this principally for your ſakes. Dos not this place begin to put on the face of Religion? you do not only profeſſe your ſelves to be Chriſtians, but many of you do believe that there is more in being a Chriſtian then a bare profeſſion, and that to be a Chriſtian is more then to be called a Chriſtian; you would pretend to be Chriſtians in the ſtricteſt ſenſe. Oh my friends, is it an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be called, and accounted a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and is it not much more an honour to be a Chriſtian? if there be any good in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Chriſtian, then labour to be ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and if there be no good in being ſo,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170271:46"/>then do not pretend to be ſo; either labour to be what you would ſeem to be, or do not pretend to be what you deſire not to be; be chriſtians in truth, or be no Chriſtians in appearance. I know you cannot hear the things which have been ſpoken to you, without ſome convictions; you muſt confeſs that your conditions have been ript up, and by what hath been ſaid, if your hearts be not in a deep ſleep, you muſt needs be ſenſible that many of you are very far from being chriſtians, and the moſt of you are but almoſt chriſtians. Are theſe things of a ſlender conſideration? can you think that this is your condition, or ſuſpect it, and yet: be quiet? nay can you choſe but trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to think what a dreadful thing it is to be but almoſt a chriſtian? ſome of you perhaps are convinc'd you are not almoſt Chriſtians yet, ſome that you are but almoſt, and ſome are ſo guilty, that you dare not put it upon the tryal, leaſt it ſhould be manifeſt that you are ſuch as the doctrine hath diſcovered. Some of you perhaps are like <hi>Gallio,</hi> you care for none of theſe things; you are reſolved to be quiet what ever the Miniſter ſays, not minding that there is a greater that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns you then the Miniſter; if we could
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170271:46"/>throw hel-fire about your ears, and ſcorch you with the heat of the Word, yet you would be quiet again ſo ſoon as you can get out of the ſight of the pulpit, and the ſound of the Miniſter; if we could cal for fire from Heaven, as <hi>Elijah</hi> did, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 1.19. Tel me, do not many of you ſit here in little eaſe? are you not ſometimes under much trouble, and under many convictions while you are under the word? but when you are out of the noiſe of that, you grow quiet again. Ah my friends, wil you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſerious, and in good earneſt? will you always be betwixt jeſt and earneſt? will you alwayes dally with convictions, and trifle with eternity? ſhall all that <hi>I</hi> have ſpoken to you from this Text be to no purpoſe? ſhall <hi>I</hi> conclude, that the Lord raiſed me up in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be a witneſſe againſt you? Pray give me leave to reaſon with you a little, and oh that the things which have been delivered to you, were written upon your hearts, that <hi>I</hi> could but make you ſenſible of the danger of that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in which many of you are. Oh that <hi>I</hi> could ſo affect my own heart, and yours in this thing, that thoſe words which <hi>Francis Spira</hi> breathed out
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170271:47"/>in his agony, might be ever ſounding in our ears; <hi>It is a fearful thing to be almoſt a Chriſtian. I</hi> beſeech you brethren enquire concerning your conditions, and compare your ſelves with the word which hath been preach'd. Gather up thoſe convictions which you have met withall in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and ſee what anſwer you can make to the Inditements which your conſciences have drawn up againſt you from it.</p>
               <p>If conſcience have not acted its part hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, let it do it now. Begin and judge your ſelves, that you be not judged of the Lord. Better it is to judge your ſelves, and lie in the duſt, then to be judged of God, and caſt into hel-fire. <hi>I</hi> would intreat all you that have at any time attempted any reformation, and pretended to a change: to conſider ſeriouſly of this thing. Are there not ſome here, who have been under great convictions of the evil of your conditions, and when theſe vvere ſtrong upon you, you made great promiſes of reforming, and of being new men. Nay, you could not conceal this, but others have taken notice of it, good people took notice of it, and they had great hopes; and wicked men took notice of it, and perhaps for preſent were ſtartled at it; but have they not ſince ſaid loe, ſee what is become of ſuch a mans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170271:47"/>the man is become like one of us again. <hi>I</hi> am confident here are thoſe amongſt us who will be ſtung to purpoſe, when they come upon their death-beds, when they do but look back, and conſider what convictions they had, what promiſes they have made, what profeſſion they have taken up for a time, and how neer they came to be Chriſtians, and how they have fallen away from their profeſſion, and are fallen to their wicked practiſes again in private, yea and ſometimes to plead for theſe evils of vvhich they have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd.</p>
               <p>Others of you that have not fallen back ſo viſibly, yet how have you ſtood ſtil, and ſhamed the hopes of <hi>Gods</hi> people, who have expected greater things from you, then they ſee, or find! It may be ſaid of ſome of you, as it was of the Galathi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>ye did run wel, who did hinder you?</hi> you ſeemed to begin in the ſpirit, but wil you end in the fleſh? you did run at firſt ſetting forth, and you were very ſenſible, and ſeemed very ſerious, but now you ſlack your pace. Is there leſſe evil in ſin now, then vvhen your eyes vvere firſt opened? you could then roar and cry, oh the evil of ſin, oh my Drunkenneſſe, my company-keeping, my Carding and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170271:48"/>Dicing; theſe were bitter things; but are theſe things leſs evil now then they were? I am ſure ſome of you have other thoughts of theſe then you had; is there leſs need of Chriſt now then in former days? or are you leſs ſenſible of it? is there leſs need of zeal for Gods glory now then before, and of circumſpection in your walking? is the ſociety of the people of God leſſe profitable, or leſſe deſirable then it was, that ſome of you vvho ſeemed to deſire opportunities of getting acquaintance with them, are at a ſtand? Look in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe things, and tel me whether theſe things do not ſpeak ſadly of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you, that you were once almoſt Chriſtians, and are now gone back, and others are but almoſt Chriſtians, and therefore ſtand at a ſtay, if you do not decline? Oh that I could perſwade you to pluck off thoſe Figg-leaves with which you cover your ſelves, and ſee the naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of your ſouls, acknowledge it, and come to Chriſt for white rayment, that your nakedneſſe do not appeare; that profeſſion which you cover your ſelves vvithall now, will be your ſhame at the laſt day.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:170271:48"/>
               <p>But here wil ariſe a great queſtion; How ſhall I know whether <hi>I</hi> am a Chriſtian in good earneſt or not, whether I am altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Chriſtian? Now, you will ſay this muſt needs be hard to reſolve, becauſe we ſin all, and every one hath ſome defects or other, and will have til we are perfected. How ſhall we be able to diſtingiſh betwixt the defects of a true Chriſtian, and one that is but almoſt a chriſtian?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A ſounde chriſtian commonly fayls in the manner of performing duties, but he that is but a chriſtian in part fails in the matter; the firſt fayls in the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials; the ſecond in the <hi>Subſtantials</hi> of duty. A ſound chriſtian performes every duty made knowen to him, the other picks and chooſes his duties, ſuch as are <hi>eaſieſt</hi> or moſt <hi>profitable</hi> or moſt in <hi>faſhion,</hi> or ſuch as are beſt <hi>accommodated</hi> to his own <hi>parts</hi> or <hi>abilities.</hi> He takes up ſome, and leaves out others; but a ſound chriſtian takes up every duty, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces all the commands of God, with equall reſpect, not having any reſpect to thoſe things which guide the other is his profeſſion and practice; <hi>The</hi> one wil performe publique duties, becauſe he can make his advantage of them; there is an honour or a profit attending them,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170271:49"/>but he neglects private duties, becauſe he can make no advantage of that which no man ſees. Or if hee doe performe private duties of prayer, and reading, yet he omits the examination of his heart, and the watching over his thoughts, and the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying of his ſecrett corruptions, becauſe theſe things are hard, and the other are more eaſie. Beſides amongſt his publick duties he performes ſome becauſe they do make moſt for the diſcovering of his abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, as a man that hath a gift in prayer, or in opening the word, may do much in them not for the love of the duties, but out of a deſire to exerciſe his owne parts: But he that is indeed a chriſtian will do all that is commanded; though it be a duty which is not fitted to his advantages, nor to w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> he is not ſitted by naturall accompliſhments, yet he wil do it willingly and cheerfully, though he can do it but weakly, this was Davids frame <hi>Pſal</hi> 119.6. <hi>Then ſhall I not be aſhamed when I have reſpect unto all thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I beſeech you conſider this. Are there not here thoſe who do pick and chooſe their duties, and that live in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant (nay total) neglect of ſuch duties, as they are convinct of? With what face can you lay claim to an intereſt in Chriſt, &amp; cal
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170271:49"/>your ſelves chriſtians? How many are there here that will take up ſome duties that are in faſhion, and yet will neglect others that have a little ſelfe denyal annext unto them? Can you be diſciples of Chriſt without fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Chriſt, nay can you be diſciples without following him with your croſſes upon your backs? <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.24. Do not flatter and deceive your ſelves, it is not every one that cryes Lord, Lord; it is not every one that calls himſelfe a Chriſtian that will be found a chriſtian at the laſt day; that which will paſs you for a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an amongſt men; wil not do it before the Lord, who judges not with mans judgment. The Lord is impartiall in judgeing; and if you be not ſo in your profeſſion, &amp; in your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, be ſure of it, the Lord will put a difference betwixt you and thoſe that fear his name.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Though all do fayle partly in the matter, and partly in manner of performing duties, yet a ſincere Chriſtian labours to finde out his defects, and to be humbled for them; but the halfe Chriſtian either ſees or conſiders them not, and therefore is quiet under them. A gracious ſoul is much in prying into its owne miſcarriages, both in its omiſſious, what duty hasbin neglected &amp;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170271:50"/>into its weakneſſes; what neglect hath bin in the duties, what grace was wanting, or what was weake in it, and ſo one duty ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes out of the aſhes of another. But the other takes noe notice of thoſe things, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents himſelf when he has done the duty, and is glad that his task is over, even as one rejoyces that he is come to his journeys end; the one ſees a reaſon to pray again, when he hath been at prayer, to begg par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for the ſins of his prayers; but the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſees no ſuch thing; the language of a carnall heart after any dutie (however it be done) is nothing but this <hi>Now ſoul take thy eaſe.</hi> Oh now tel me, be there not many that live in the neglect of duties, publick, and private, family and cloſet duties, and yet you are quiet under them? this is ſad e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence that you are of theſe halfe chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. If you were truly humbled, ii were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that you ſhould pleaſe your ſelves in ſuch a poſture; it is impoſſible for a man or woman to continue reſolvedly in that for which he is truely humbled: that which thou groaneſt under, thou wilt labour to lay downe and if thou art not humbled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy defects, thou art no Chriſtan; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member and conſider it all you that hear me this day, it is a thing in conſiſtent with the truth of chriſtianitie for a man to live in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170271:50"/>a willing, quiet, conſtant neglect of any known duty. The beſt Chriſtian may be be put by the performance of his known duty: by the ſtrength of ſome temptation for a time; but to perſiſt in this, to make this his conſtant practice, and quiet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in it, is a notorious proof of a half Chriſtian. But this let me ſay to you, vvho are complaining of your failings in duty, and are deeply ſenſible of your wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drings, and weakneſſe, and your ſouls are afflicted for them, and you are filled from hence with humble thoughts of your ſelves; God vvil put a difference betwixt your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and other mens. Be of good com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, you ſhal not be reckoned amongſt theſe halters, and halfers in the vvorſhip of God; you that make this daily uſe of the imperfections of your duties to lie lovv, and humble before the Lord, ſhall never be charged vvith them in the vvorld to come. And you that can neither think well, nor ſpeak wel of your ſelves in what you do, you ſhal have this honor, &amp; this comfort, to hear wel of God, and ſhal have this teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that you have pleaſed him, when you ſhal have the great ſeal of Gods appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation ſet upon your weak, but ſincere o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, <hi>Well done you good and faithful ſervant.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:170271:51"/>
               <p>He that is but <hi>almost a Christian</hi> is unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to find out his duty, though he dare not live out of the practice of it, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd; but he that is <hi>altogether a Chriſtian,</hi> does not onely live in the <hi>practice</hi> of what he <hi>knows,</hi> but is greedy to <hi>know</hi> what he ought to <hi>practiſe.</hi> It is not ſo much the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving up to what we know, as the deſire to know how we ſhould live, that does evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence a man to be a ſound and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial chriſtian. It is poſſible to find a man that neglects no known duty, and yet is but half a Chriſtian, for conſcience may be ſo awakened, that a man may not dare to neglect any thing which he is convinc'd he ought to do, being known he muſt practice it, for his peace ſake; but this man is not willing to know his duty, he wil not take it up til it be clearly brought home to him, he wil not ſeek for it, and hunt after it, he wil ſtop his ears and eys as long as he can, but when he can withſtand the hints, and intimations, and convictions no longer, then he cannot but take it up: but he that is a true Chriſtian does not onely practiſe what he knows, but he deſires to know that he may practiſe; he ſeeks out for his duty, which a hypocrite wil not do; the hypocrite ſeeks for his peace in the performance of duty, but the godly man
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170271:51"/>ſeeks out for his duty; if he have the leaſt hint in the Word of any duty which he hath been ignorant of, he cannot be quiet til he be ſatisfied about it, til he hath found it out. The other does not more greedily ſuck in comfort and notious tending that way, then he dos information of duty and directions about it.</p>
               <p>Now let me tel you the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween thoſe two ſorts of perſons is not more eminently diſcerned in any thing then in this <hi>I</hi> am ſpeaking unto. For the higheſt pitch that ſuch a man can come to who is not fully a Chriſtian, is this, that he may live in the practiſe of every known duty, yet here he is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from a ſound, hearty, ſubſtantial Chriſtian; there is in him an unwilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to be informed, and convinced of his duty. There does remain in every un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regenerate man, (and is the ſureſt mark of unregeneracy,) an unwilingneſs to come to the light, leaſt their deeds ſhould be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered. Natural conſcience, and legal working wil make a man follow the light when once it hath found him out, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but grace wil make a man love the light, and ſeek after the light to walk by it, <hi>John</hi> 3.20, 21. Give me leave to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend this particular to your conſideration,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170271:52"/>and take heed you be not deceived here. Here are ſome of you come to the Word, and perhaps God meets with you, and convinces you of a ſin, and you go away, and reſolve againſt it; nay perhaps you make conſcience of that ever after; again you are convinc'd of ſuch a duty, and go home, and take up ſome reſolutions to practice it, nay you cannot be quiet in the neglect of it, and you wil ſay, ſurely I am now a Chriſtian indeed, for I live in the Commiſſion of no known ſin, nor in the omiſſion of any known duty; do <hi>I</hi> lack any thing yet? this is enough for to make thee paſs for a true Chriſtian with others, but this doth not make thee ſo before the Lord, neither mayeſt thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude thy ſelf ſuch a one from all this; thou mayeſt be almoſt a Chriſtian all this while; for the maine thing may yet be wanting, which is, grace in the heart; thou mayeſt not neglect duty, and yet thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not love thy duty; thou mayeſt not dare to diſobey the command, and yet thou mayeſt not delight in the commands of God; if thou haſt nothing but convictions and awakenings of conſcience, thou wilt never hunt after thy duty, ſeek abroad for it as <hi>Eſau</hi> hunted for the veniſon; thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, when it is brought home to thee, and preſt upon thee, wilt receive it as <hi>Jacob</hi> did the Kids fleſh upon his Mothers importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170271:52"/>Oh tel me, are you not troubled when you meet with a conviction under the Word, and you ſtruggle againſt it, and would fain evade it; you would not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſee your ſin, nor willingly ſee your duty. Nay, when you do meet with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of either kind, your hearts do riſe againſt it, and you ſay in your ſelves, Oh that this were no ſin, that I might enjoy it quietly, or oh that there were no ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to make this my duty; ſo that though you yeeld to the conviction, and walk by it, yet you are ſurprized by it; the duty finds out you, you do not find out that, nor go forth to meet it half way; this is a clear ſign you are not come fully up to cloſe with Chriſt; there is as great a difference betwixt you and one that is come fully to the termes of Chriſt, as there is betwixt green wood and dry; the greeneſt wood may be made to burn if it be put into the fire &amp; much blown upon, but the dry wood takes fire preſently without the help of the bellows. A godly heart is like Tinder, the leaſt ſpark of conviction that falls upon it kindles it, he complies as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily with the word of conviction, as with the words of comfort; nay ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily catches hold of the former, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves it more then the latter. <hi>Balam</hi> was ſo
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170271:53"/>convinc'd of ſin, that he dares not go be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the command of God; but his beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour may prove, that the diſcoveries which God made to him, did not pleaſe him. But <hi>David</hi> dos not onely follow a conviction, but loves it, and loves the means by which he was convinc'd, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.10, 11. <hi>With my whole heart have I ſought thee, O let me not wander from thy Commandements; thy word have I hid in my heart that I might not ſin againſt thee, Pſalm</hi> 19.11. <hi>David</hi> counted the word ſweet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, becauſe it gave him warning con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſin that he might avoid it, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it enlightned his eyes, and ſhewed him his duty that he might practice it, <hi>v.</hi> 8. Surely an hypocrite cannot love the word of God upon this account, theſe are not the breathings of unſound hearts; they ſay nor as he did, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.5. <hi>O that my ways wore directe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l to keep thy ſtatutes!</hi> They pray not as he did, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.27.33, 34, 36. <hi>Make me to underſtand the way of thy precepts: Teach me, O LORD, the way of thy statutes: Give me underſtanding, and I ſhall keep thy law: Incline mine heart unto thy teſtimonies.</hi> They have not his affections, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.14, 16, 20, 72. <hi>I have rejoyced in the way of thy testimonies, as much as in all riches, I will delight my ſelf in thy ſtatutes:
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170271:53"/>I wil not forget thy word, My ſoul breaketh for the longing that it hath unto thy judgements at all times. The law of thy mouth is better unto me then thouſands of gold and ſilver.</hi> Theſe are the great and infallible charecters of a heart fully complying with God, of one that is a Chriſtian, and Diſciple of Chriſt indeed; the man or woman that does thus is doubtleſs ſuch a one as <hi>David</hi> prayed he might be. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.80. his heart is ſound with God; but if it be otherwiſe with you, <hi>I</hi> tel you you are not yet the Diſciples of Chriſt, you do not follow him in that great thing, in which he is propoſed as our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample <hi>(viz.)</hi> he did not onely do his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wil, but he counted it meat &amp; drink to do ſo.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He that is a Chriſtian indeed, labours to be much more a Chriſtian then yet he is; he that is but <hi>almoſt a Chriſtian,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents himſelf with what he is, and thinks all is wel; and indeed this is a ſure diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of both theſe. They who are <hi>altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chriſtians,</hi> I mean in reſpect of their <hi>perſwaſions</hi> and <hi>endeavours,</hi> account them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves but <hi>half Chriſtians</hi> in reſpect of <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice</hi> and attainment: But he that is but half a Chriſtian both in practice and in perſwaſion, accounts himſelf enough in both. I have heard this complaint fall
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170271:54"/>from the mouth often of one of the emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenteſt chriſtians that ever I knew, <hi>I</hi> am but half a chriſtian. But I never hear you for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malluke-warm profeſſors ſo judg of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Theſe are much in obſerving the difference betwixt them and others, rather then the diſproportion that is betwixt them and others, and that great example by which they are to walk, and that holy Law unto which they are to be conformed, whereas a true chriſtian is much in comparing himſelf with the Law of God, humbling himſelf for falling ſhort of that, and not applauding himſelf for that in which he ſeems to exceed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; now that you may the better judge of your ſelves by this tryal laid down, I ſhal help you a little by branching this Head into theſe four particulars; for there is none that wil ſeem guilty of this at firſt ſight, but wil ſay, I would be more a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian then I am, and I wiſh I were better, and pray God make us all better, and yet ſuch perſons have a ſecret opinion of their condition that it is good enough, and they ſtrive not to be better: you ſhall know whether you do reckon your ſelves altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chriſtians or not, by theſe four things.</p>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:170271:54"/>
               <p n="1">1. If the performance, ſome duties take thee off from the enquiry after others; thus it is wit ha half chriſtian, he makes one duty a vail to cover another, he makes one duty a blinde to another, and becauſe he does ſome things which others neglect, he thinks he does all that is required. Thus it was with the Phariſee, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.12. <hi>I thank God I am not as other men.</hi> And thus it was with <hi>Paul</hi> before converſion, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Touching the righteouſneſſe which is in the law blameleſſe.</hi> But a true chriſtian is careful that while he performs ſome duties, he does not neglect others, and he carries a jealouſie over himſelf ſtil, that he hath not found out the duties of every conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and of every relation, he fears ſtil that ſomething of his duty is hîd from his eyes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A man that thinks himſelf to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough a chriſtian, does not onely think that he doth enough, but he thinks he does every thing wel enough, he thinks that he is ſpiritual enough in duty; but the other labours to be more ſpiritual in what he does. So that he does not only deſire to abound in the matter of duty, but ſo excel in the manner of performing it.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:170271:55"/>
               <p n="3">3. He that thinks himſelf enough a Chriſtian, looks not unto Jeſus Chriſt his pattern and example, but he looks to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to others that are beneath him, and this confirms him in opinion of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: and hence it is, that he is not hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled under his failings, but lifted up under his performances. But a true chriſtian that thinks himſelf but a piece of a chriſtian, and would be much more ſuch, is much in eying Chriſt, and is much in humbling himſelf for falling ſhort of him in every thing that he does. If he looks to men, it is to them that excel him in grace; but he looks more to Chriſt, then to all men li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, as the Apoſtle did, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12, 13, 14. <hi>Not as though I had already attained, either were already perfect: but I follow after, if that I way apprehend that for which alſo I am ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended of Chriſt. Brethren, I count not my ſelf to have apprehended: but this one thing I do, forgetting thoſe things that are behind, and reaching forth unto thoſe things which are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I preſs toward the mark, for the price of the high calling of God in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. He that thinks himſelf enough a chriſtian, wil ſhew himſelf in this, he is not willing to receive any conviction from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one concerning his condition; he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170271:55"/>beare with any one that will deal plainly with him, and call his condition into queſtion; he is ſhy of ſuch as are faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full with him, and offended at any word that ſeemes to be preſt upon him; he thinks he does not deſerve it. But a ſound Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian takes it kindly, when any deale faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with him, and he receives every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof or conviction with much tenderneſs; nay he is not offended if any doe ſuſpect or feare his condition <hi>conſcientiouſly,</hi> though perhaps <hi>cauſleſly,</hi> and the reaſon why he can bear with the feares and jealouſies of others is becauſe he hath jealouſies of himſelf. By theſe things you ſhall try your own ſpirits whether you do account your ſelves enough Chriſtians. If upon inquiry you finde that you have this eſteeme of your ſelves, then know that you are no chriſtians indeed, and in truth. For he that is a chriſtian fully in perſwaſion, deſires ſtil to be more a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian in practiſe; he is not and cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with what he is, nor with what he does, but labours as much to exceed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as the others doth labour to exceede others; he labours to have his laſt workes more then his former, where as the other contents himſelfe in running his rounde, &amp; in doing to day, as yeſterday, and to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row as this day.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:170271:56"/>
               <p n="5">5. He that is but almoſt a chriſtian dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers from a ſound in this: he wil follow <hi>God</hi> no farther then to get quiet of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the other follows <hi>God</hi> for holineſs. Now a deſire to pacifie a troubled conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence may carry a man far; but a deſire to be holy wil carry a man much farther, and the reaſon is evident. Becauſe the one is a conſtrained motion, the other is free and voluntary. A man that is acted meerly by a deſire of peace, wil not go ſo far as he that is moved by an inward principle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not converſant in duty for the love of duty, but for the love of his peace, which if he miſs, he wil after a time caſt aſide the duty as vaine and unprofitable; or if he meet with it, he wil begin to be more remiſs in it, counting it needleſs to be ſo ſtrict, when he hath attained his ends. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, ſuch a man wil limit himſelf in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that ſeeks nothing but his peace in it; he wil go no farther then he ſees he muſt go, or hazard his peace; and when he hath quieted his conſcience, by arriving at ſuch a meaſure of reformation, and by attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſuch a degree of profeſſion, he then reſolves to ſit down, and ſays, All is wel. Every motion ceaſes in the attaining the end of it; ſo does this mans endeavour, when he hath gotten a little reſt to his
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170271:56"/>ſpirit; but a man that follows God for holineſſe can never be ſatisfied with it; he cannot ſit down and ſay it is enough; for he can never have the fil of his deſire in this life; there is an infiniteneſs in the deſire of every renewed heart after God, and holineſs, which cannot be filled up til it come in Heaven. We have a very plain ſcripture for this, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.23. Belov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, now are we the ſons of God, and it doth not yet appeare what we ſhal be; but vve know that when he ſhal appeare, we ſhal be like him, for we ſhal ſee him as he is that hath this hope, purifies himſelf as <hi>God</hi> is pure; here is a ſure rule to judge of the truth of our deſires by. He that deſires ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs unfaignedly and ſincerely, deſires it infinitely; but he that deſires it for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, deſires it but in a ſuch a degree as wil ſerve to reach ſuch an end as he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to himſelf, if a man ſeeks it for his or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in the world, then he ſeeks no more of it then is in credit with men. If he ſeek it for his peace, then he ſeeks it onely ſo far as may ſerve to allay the heate of his conſcience, and to remove ſuch convictions that are upon him; and when this is done, he ſtrives no farther. What a man uſes as a meanes to another thing, which is the end, he ſeaſes to uſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170271:57"/>when he hath attained that for which he uſed it; but what a man deſires ſimply for it ſelf, that he deſires ſtil, ſo long as it is abſent in any degree; this is one reaſon why covetous men are never ſatisfied with riches, becauſe they deſire them for themſelves. A covetous man makes rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es his end, and he can never be ſatisfied unleſſe he had all. A godly man makes Gods glory his end, and uſes riches but as a meanes to this; ſo that if he have but enough to help him in this deſign, to attain his end of honouring God, he is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied; as good men ſeek riches and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, ſo do wicked men ſeek grace and holineſs in their notions; they ſeek theſe as meanes to ſome other thing, they would have ſome grace, as much as would ſerve their turn to hold up their credit in the world, or to keep the worm of conſcience from gnawing now, or as much as they think will bring them to Heaven; but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle wil ſerve for the firſt, &amp; they think a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle wil ſerve for the laſt, and therefore they would not have much; they would not be too ſtrict, nor too preciſe to trouble the world, nor have people think that they are ſingular, yet they would be counted good Chriſtians; let me tel you as many of you as limit your ſelves, and ſet ſuch and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170271:57"/>ſuch bounds to your profeſſion and deſires, and think a meaſure of grace and holineſs is enough; you think you are good chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans as you need be, yea and as good as you deſire to be, it is manifeſt you do not make grace and holineſs your end, but you deſire it for ſomething elſe, it is but a meanes to ſome other thing, which you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving attained, reſt in; if you did ſeek grace and holineſs for it ſelf, you could not poſſibly reſt in any degree of it which is attainable here; you would never ſit down and ſay you had enough, til you were holy, even as God is holy. If you did ſeek God aright in an ordinance, you would not onely ſeek the knowledge of him, but conformity to him. A carnal heart may deſire the knowledge of God, but a regenerate ſeeks to have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him; the one would know the truth, but the other would experience it; one would not be ignorant of God, but the other he would not be without God, he makes it his buſineſs to enjoy God, and til he do ſo, nothing wil ſatisfie him.</p>
               <p>But now leaſt <hi>I</hi> ſhould wound any poor doubting ſoul with that which was inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded onely to awaken you, and ſend ſuch a one away grieved from this ordinance, and ſtrengthen thoſe ſad concluſions
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170271:58"/>which ſuch a one is to ready to draw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelf; I ſhal lay down a few things for the ſatisfaction of ſuch, which may ſtay their ſouls with ſome comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſwaſion, that they are not the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple intended in the convictions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs which have been laid down in this Doctrine. Tel me then thou doubting ſoul who feareſt greatly concerning thy condition, and art jealous that thou art but almoſt a chriſtian, anſwer me the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion which I ſhal propound unto thee, and I truſt thou wilt be able to unty this knot which is upon thy ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Art thou willing to know all the wil of God? is there in thee an impartial de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be acquainted with every command, and to have all the light to ſhine in thy face? Doeſt thou not deſire to ſhrowd thy ſelf under any cloud of darkneſſe and ignorance of the minde of God, nor to ſhift off any convictions of the truth, and of thy duty contained in it? if thou doen love the light, yea all the light, convincing as wel as comforting light, this ſpeaks com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably to thee, as to a ſoul that is ſound in the ſtatutes of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Doeſt thou find thy heart complying with every command of God, when it is made known to thee? canſt thou ſay with
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170271:58"/>
                  <hi>David,</hi> that <hi>thou haſt reſpect to all his ways?</hi> art thou glad when thou getteſt more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſin, that thou mayeſt eſcape it, and more light concerning thy duty, that thou mayeſt embrace it? this is a ſigne that the Law is written in thy heart, and thy heart wil not be removed from it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Do thy endeavours witneſs the truth of thy deſires? art thou willing to uſe every means which God has appointed to bring thee to that end, which thou ſayeſt thou propoſeſt to thy ſelf? Many are full of wiſhes and wouldings; they will ſay We muſt be holy, and we muſt be thus and thus, and pray God we may be ſo, and pray God turn our hearts, but theſe are idle wiſhes, they are not accompanied with the uſe of every meanes which is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to this end. They would wiſh that God would make them ſuch and ſuch, but ſtil they continue in their ſhops, when they ſhould be in the publick Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, or in private duties, and they link themſelves to ſuch company where they cannot expect ſuch things as they pretend to deſire. They neglect to joyn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the people of God, who might fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch deſignes; this is an argument their deſires are not deſignes, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170271:59"/>but if thou doſt uſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> every meanes which God hath appointed as a furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of holineſs; this does teſtifie for thee that thy deſires after holineſs are true and unfeigned.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Doeſt thou deſire to exerciſe every grace as wel as to perform every duty? doſt thou endeavour to fil up thy duties with grace? this is the great diſcovery of a Chriſtian indeed, who does not content himſelf to performe duties in a ſlight and formal manner, but does labour to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe that grace which is required in the duty, and does account this the ornament of duty, when much grace is exerciſed in it. He is not ſatisfied with parts and gifts, and the enlargement of theſe in prayer, meditation, or conference; but he looks to the frame of the heart, and rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces when he finds that ſet right for God Is this thy deſire, &amp; thy great deſign in every duty? oh this may be a good evidence for thee that thou art a Chriſtian in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Doſt thou bleſſe God ſimply for the change that is wrought upon thy ſoul? he that is a Chriſtian indeed rejoyces more in the change which is begun in his ſoul, then in any thing that is here below; he that hath been truly humbled for ſin,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170271:59"/>and grieved for that, rejoyces principally in ſanctification, and bleſſes God for that; he that was never truly humbled for ſin, can rejoyce, and thank God he is not as other men; but it is rather a boaſting, then a thankſgiving, he can rejoyce in the fruits of ſuch a change as is wrought in him; he comforts himſelf in this, that there are many worſe then he, and that people look upon him with another eye then they do other men; this he rejoyces in, becauſe it is for honour, but he rejoyces not ſimply in grace and holineſs; for then he would mourn for others who want it, and not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt himſelf; he may rejoyce alſo becauſe he hath gotten a little quiet in his own ſpirit by the change which ſeems to be in him, and he ſays it is better now then in former times, yet he may not rejoyee ſimply be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is changed, for then he would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be more and more changed from grace to grace; but a true chriſtian rejoyce; in the beginnings of ſanctification with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect to any by conſiderations, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny advantages which may come to him by it. Tel me, do you rejoyce with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliſt becauſe your profeſſion has gotten you a little repute in the world, or a little quiet in, your conſciences? or do you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce with the people of God, that you are
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170271:60"/>more ſpiritual in duty, more humble, more mortified to the world, more like to God in every faculty of the ſoul, and moreen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged to him in all your affections; this is the true and proper joy of Gods people; it is not peace, but purity that pleaſes them their comforts do increaſe but as their grace doth encreaſe; as they get more grace, ſo they get more joy, becauſe nothing comforts them but the renewing of their ſouls, according to the image of God in Chriſt Jeſus; now if this be the riſe of thy joy, this is a good witneſs for thee that thou art a chriſtian indeed.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Doeſt thou not reſt in that meaſure of grace which thou ſeemeſt to have, but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boureſt after an infinite holineſſe, to <hi>perfect holineſs in the fear of God?</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. and to <hi>be holy as God is holy.</hi> If it be thus, thou art a chriſtian indeed, and thy hope which thou haſt for Heaven, is a true hope. 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.3. For he <hi>that hath this hope in him, purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf as he is pure.</hi> He is not the trueſt Chriſtian that ſeemeth to have moſt, but he that really deſires, and deſignes for moſt; for the Lord mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures us by theſe; the hungring chriſtian is the ſound chriſtian; therefore <hi>bleſſed,</hi> yea undoubtedly <hi>bleſſed are they that</hi> thus
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170271:60"/>
                  <hi>hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſs,</hi> who have a kind of infiniteneſs in their deſires after God and his holineſs, and can ſay truly that their deſires after this do exceed their deſires after all other things.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Canſt thou make thy appeals for thy principles, that they are ſpiritual as wel as thy actions? that thou art not moved by baſe, &amp; low, and carnal intereſt in what thou doeſt, but it is the honour of God, the love of his ways and holineſſe that acts thee in thy general courſe? many may do much for God, and yet carry their own intereſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, as <hi>Jehu</hi> did; but if thy ends be for God as wel as thy actions, then thou art a Chriſtian altogether.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Canſt thou appeale to God for thy ſincerity before him? doeſt thou not look to men ſo much as to God in thy profeſſion, and labour to commend thy ſelf to them, but to God chiefly and mainly, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureſt in every thing to approve thy ſelf to him? If it be thus, then know, that though thou haſt many imperfections, and faileſt in every thing that thou doeſt, yet thou art altogether a Chriſtian; thou art perfect in the perfection of the goſpel, though not in the perfection of the Law. I may invert that ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>Philip.</hi> 8.15.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170271:61"/>He ſayes as many as are perfect are thus minded; I may ſay as many as are thus minded are perfect; this is the perfection which the Goſpel requires and accepts; but if you come not up to a goſpel-perfection, all your profeſſion and performances are in vain; for know that the goſpel requires its perfection as ſtrictly as the law did; only with this difference; the law required per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect obedience in act, the goſpel accepts ſincere obedience in act, and perfect in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and endeavour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>A <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of Caution.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>USE</hi> 3. The third and laſt Uſe ſhal be of caution to all, that you reſt not in ſuch half perſwaſions; and in hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng this, I ſhal lay down firſt, ſome quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening motives, and ſecondly, conclude with ſome directions. I have ſpoken ſomething in general to the uſe of the point. I ſhall draw toward a concluſion, when I have laid down a few motives to quicken you all to the particular applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the truth, and to a careful avoiding
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170271:61"/>of that evil temper which I have diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the text. I have ſhown you that a man may be almoſt a chriſtian, and yet never truly ſuch; I have ſhewen you what it is to be ſuch. <hi>I</hi> ſhall now ſhewe you the evil of being ſuch. <hi>I</hi> know ſome of you are or have bin convinced, that this is your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and yet you are quiet againe, <hi>I</hi> ſhal nowe lay down a few things as motives to awaken your convictions, and to rowſe you yet if it be poſſible, out of that ſlum bering ſtate in which you are; <hi>I</hi> ſhould be loath to leave you aſleepe after all that <hi>I</hi> have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, leaſt you ſhould ſleepe the ſleepe of death.</p>
               <p>Firſt, conſider if you are not <hi>altogether Chriſtians,</hi> you are then <hi>altogether no Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> all your labour is loſt, your profeſſion wil come to nothing, all that you have done will not profit you, you ſhal be reckoned among the heathen, and ſuch as have not knowen God. Chriſt will one day profeſs to you that he knowes you not, all your bodily labour and externall profeſſion, though it ſhould be accompanied with ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo great expence &amp; charge in the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, wil not be reckoned of, if your hearts be not right before God. We find notable expreſſion of the Lord to Solomon
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170271:62"/>when he had built the Lord a temple, with a vaſt expence of treaſure, and had ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed two and twenty thouſand oxen, and a hundred and twenty thouſand ſheepe, which was a very large ſervice, then the Lord appeares to him 1. <hi>King</hi> 9.4. and ſayes thus, <hi>If thou wilt walk before me as thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther David walked in integrity of heart and uprightneſs, to do all that I have commanded thee, and wilt keep my ſtatutes and my iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then I will eſtabliſh the throne of thy kingdom upon Iſrael for ever.</hi> Mark what a ſeaſonable caution the Lord gives Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, think not now thou haſt done enough becauſe thou haſt done all this for the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my houſe; for although thou haſt done very largly, and haſt bin very magnificent in my ſervice, yet know that all this will not ſerve my turn, if thy heart be not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right before me; all this vvill not profit thee nor this people that glory in it; if thou ſhalt ſtick at other of my commands, it will not avayl thee that thou haſt obeyed me in this thing.</p>
               <p>If thou doſt not obey in all things, all thy obedience is nothing worth; yea though it may ſeem much, yet if truly weighed, it is
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170271:62"/>very little. I ſhall inſiſt a little upon this becauſe it ariſes naturally from the words; and here ſhall endeavour to prove that he that is but almoſt a Chriſtian, is but the leaſt part of a Chriſtian. If we compare the words of the text with Pauls anſwer to it, we ſhall finde that this ſenſe may be ſafely put upon the ſame, which <hi>I</hi> hinted in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening the words. I told you (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) which is here rendred almoſt or within a little, may as well be rendred <hi>in that which is little:</hi> I am perſwaded to be a Chriſtian, or <hi>I am a little perſwaded.</hi> I could in ſome things be content to be a Chriſtian, but not in all. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeemes to take him in this ſenſe by his reply which is, I wiſh thou were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> as wel in much as in little, as well in greater matters as in leſs, ſuch as <hi>I</hi> am. This is the caſe of many men under the word; they have ſome convictions upon them, and ſome perſwaſions wrought in them, and they would compounde with Chriſt, they would follow him in ſome things, but not in all; and they would be Chriſtians in ſome things, but not in others; and theſe things unto which they are perſwaded to yeeld, and in which
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170271:63"/>they wil comply, they are but little things, and though they ſeem to be altogether Chriſtians to ſome, and almoſt ſuch to all; yet they are but the leaſt part of a chriſtian all the while; he that comes neareſt to a chriſtian, and is not ſo altogether, is very far from being a chriſtian: though convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and perſwaſions may be ſtrong in ſuch as are not yet regenerated, and they may go very far (as <hi>I</hi> have ſhewed you in opening the Doctrine.) Nay if they ſhould go ſo far, as to give their goods to the poor, and their bodies to the fire, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch things, which may ſeem very glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in the eyes of men, yet let all that ſuch men do be ſeriouſly weighed and conſidered, and you ſhal find it exceeding ſmal. The moſt glorious hypocrite in the world, and the cunningeſt formaliſt that hath put on the outſide of Religion, and in many things can hardly be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be ſuch, is lighter then vanity it ſelf, compared with a true Chriſtian. Though theſe are like <hi>Saul</hi> among the people, taller by the head and ſhoulders, yet ſet him amongſt Chriſtians, and he is a Dwarf; and though he may be of great eſteem for a Chriſtian with ſome, yet he is ſtil a Chriſtian onely in little things. Now this is that which I ſhall labour to make
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170271:63"/>plaine and evident unto you, it being my great deſigne in this to pull down the high and lofty ſpirits of formal and emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty profeſſors, who content themſelves to vvalk in a ſtinted profeſſion, and whiles they look to ſome things in which they exceed many others, (as to ſome common works of conviction which they have had, and to ſome meaſure of perſwaſion, and to their outward profeſſion) they think themſelves to be ſome body, they are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, &amp; they think they do much vvhen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they do little. The Apoſtle ſpeaking of the performances of hypocrites, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.2. ſays expreſly, if this were all that he had to ſhew to prove himſelf a Chriſtian, he were not <hi>only little, but nothing. All theſe without grace would make me nothing.</hi> Theſe are great things with ſome men, and would make a man paſſe for ſuch; but theſe things wil not make a man ſeem any thing before the Lord; and if we look upon ſuch aright, they vvil ſeem little to us, which I ſhal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate four ways.</p>
               <div n="1" type="demonstration">
                  <head>
                     <hi>DEMONSTRATION</hi> 1.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. A formaliſt is a Chriſtian in little things, becauſe he does but little in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of Chriſt, who is his pattern, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.6. <hi>He that ſaies he abides in Christ, ought to walk as he walked.</hi> Now if we compare the half-chriſtian with Jeſus Chriſt, who is
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170271:64"/>an example of holineſs, unto whom every one that is called after his name ſhould be conformed, we ſhal finde him to be emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and lame indeed; it would require much time to compare the life of ſuch a perſon with Chriſt in particulars. But you wil ſay, If we compare the beſt mens lives with Chriſt, they wil be found to fal ſhort as wel as he, and the ſtrongeſt chriſtians wil be as nothing in compariſon of him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> Though the beſt chriſtians have cauſe to be humbled for their failings, when they look to Chriſt whom they are to follow, yet there is a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe and the formaliſt in this thing. For though there be a ſeeming conformity in every hypocrite to Chriſt, yet it is but in appearance, not in reality, but there is a real and ſincere conformity to Chriſt in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very true chriſtian.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Though there be ſome likeneſs, yet there is more unlikeneſs to Chriſt in the half-chriſtian; but in the true chriſtian, though there be ſome unlikeneſs, yet there is more likeneſs; for firſt, though they have fleſh as wel as ſpirit, and a part unregene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate as wel as regenerate, yet the ſpirit doth prevail over the fleſh, and the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate over the unregenerate, ſo that this may, and does ſtil paſſe for the principal
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170271:64"/>part: it is not ſo with the formaliſt; for at the beſt he is carnal, and altogether fleſh.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, though he fails in every du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and there is ſome corruption mixed with what he does, yet there is ſomething of Chriſt in every duty, and this weighs down all his corruption; but in a formaliſt there is nothing of Chriſt in any duty that he performs; though he may exerciſe parts, and have great enlargements, yet there is nothing of grace in it, and ſo no conformity to Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, though there be a great difference betwixt the actions of Chriſt and a chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, in reſpect of the perfection required in the Law (Chriſt did every thing accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the righteouſneſs of the Law) yet in reſpect of that perfection which the goſpel admits of, there is not ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion betwixt the obedience of Chriſt and a chriſtian. If the Law were to be judge of this, it would caſt away all that a beleever does, and conclude it <hi>no way like</hi> to what Chriſt hath done, becauſe <hi>not every way like it:</hi> but let the goſpel judge it, and it will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge a great conformity in the one to the other, <hi>Romans</hi> 8.29. yea there is ſuch a conformity in a beleever to
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170271:65"/>Chriſt, that he is accounted perfect, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Let us therefore. as many as be perfect, be thus minded.</hi> The work of holineſſe in him is ſo deemed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1. <hi>Perfecting ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs in the fear of God;</hi> and particular gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are pronounced perfect, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.5. all theſe are in the goſpel acceptation: ſo that with the favourable interpretation of the goſpel, you ſee a beleever is very like to Chriſt who is his pattern; but all the grace and favour that the goſpel doth ſhew to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, cannot ſo help a formaliſt, to make him to appeare like to Chriſt in this ſenſe.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Though in all things he does not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to that meaſure of perfection to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to walk as Chriſt walked, yet in his deſires and deſignes he is ſo; there is the ſame minde in him that was in Chriſt; take the inner man of the heart, and you ſhall find it exactly like to Chriſt, renewed in knowledge, and in grace alſo according to his image, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.10. <hi>John</hi> 1.16. <hi>Of his ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs have we all received grace for grace.</hi> Look to his principles, and they are the ſame, love to God, and to the word of God, and wil of God; this is his meat and drink, as it was Chriſts, <hi>John</hi> 4.34. Thus it was with <hi>David, Pſalm</hi> 119.97. <hi>O how love I thy law, it is my meditation all the day.</hi>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:170271:65"/>Look to his ends, they are like Chriſts, the honour and glory of God, and the good of other ſouls, as we find, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21.24. <hi>But to me to live is Chriſt, and to die is gain. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, to abide in the fleſh is more needful for you.</hi> So that all things conſidered, there is more agreement and conformity betwixt the life of Chriſt and a true chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, then there is diſagreement, or non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity; they agree in more then they do differ in; but the life of a halting chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is ſo far ſhort of following, that he is not any way like him; ſo that upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, he that is but almoſt a Chriſtian does very little in all that he does, becauſe it is no way proportioned to the life of Chriſt, which is the copy after which every chriſtian muſt write.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="demonstration">
                  <head>
                     <hi>DEMONST.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <p>As all that ſuch a man does, is but little in compariſon of Chriſt whom he is to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate: ſo alſo it is but little in compariſon of what the Saints do; he comes very far ſhort of the very weakeſt of the people of God, in theſe two particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In actual performances; weigh what he does, and it is little to what a true chriſtian does.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Look to his deſires and deſigns, and they fal yet more abundantly ſhort.</p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:170271:66"/>
                  <p n="1">1. To their performances: and a man that is truly wrought upon, ſticks at no du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he yeelds obedience to all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of God impartially; but the other profeſſes with reſerves, and yeelds obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with reſpect to credit, or eaſe, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, or the peace of his own conſcience, and ſuch a man wll not, cannot go ſo far as a ſound and throughly perſwaded chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He does not onely do all that is commanded, but he exerciſeth ſome grace in every thing that he doth; and upon this account it may be truly ſaid, the leaſt true beleever does more in the leaſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous performance then all the formaliſts, and half chriſtians in the world do, if they were all put together. What was the reaſon that the Widdows mite vvas greater then all the Phariſees great gifts? becauſe there vvas grace in that gift, this raiſed the value of it ſo much; ſo the leaſt exerciſe of grace is more then all the guilded performances of theſe half-chriſtians: Though theſe can pray, and hear, and preach, and diſcourſe, and give alms, yet they cannot exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe any grace in theſe, there is nothing of Chriſt in theſe; and therefore they are of no value. One duty of a true beleever hath
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170271:66"/>more weight and worth in it, then all that ſuch men ever did, or vvil do (while they are ſuch) to the end of the world.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, as they fal ſhort of the Saints in action, ſo much more in deſigne; for in this there is no more compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a formal half-chriſtian, and a ſound chriſtian, then is betwixt finite and infinite; for the deſire and aime of a gracious ſoul as <hi>I</hi> have ſhewen you, is after infinite holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; it knows no bounds, and therefore cannot be compared with any thing that is limited, and bounded within a compaſſe, as the perſwaſions and profeſſions of one that is but <hi>almoſt a Chriſtian</hi> are. Now though the Law takes no notice of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, or of deſires, or deſignes to do a thing that is not done, but looks only to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which is the perfection of intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: yet the goſpel ſets a high eſteem upon this vvhere it is ſound and true; and the Lord accepts this, and eſteemes it as if it vvere brought forth into act, as in <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.18. yea and he meaſures actions by this, as being a ſupplement unto them; yea this makes ſmal things ſeeme very great, vvhen they are vveighed, becauſe they were done vvith great deſire and affection, and in a deſigne to ſome greater
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170271:67"/>thing. Upon this account there is no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion betwixt the deſires and deſignes of one that is but almoſt a chriſtian, and him that is altogether ſuch; for the latter hath a greater reach with him in all that he doth, &amp; docs as far exceed him, as that which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite does exceed that which is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="demonstration">
                  <head>
                     <hi>DEMONS.</hi> 3.</head>
                  <p>He that is but almoſt a chriſtian, does but little, if you compare what he does with what he omits. He ſeems to do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, but all that he does is not like that which he omits, which wil be manifeſt upon theſe two accounts.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. He does fewer things then he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. He performs ſmal things, and omits great. Perhaps he may be ſaid to do many things with <hi>Herod, Mark</hi> 6.20. that is in compariſon of former days; he began to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve many things which he made light of before, but theſe many things compared with the things which he ought to have done, would ſeem a very few. This I could eaſily ſhew you, if <hi>I</hi> ſhould open the life of a chriſtian, and the duties of it, and ſhew you how exceeding broad the commands of <hi>God</hi> are; and when you did ſee how vvide and deep theſe are, you would eaſily
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170271:67"/>ſee how ſhort and weak ſuch a mans obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is; but this wil be too large a task at this time: yet <hi>I</hi> ſhal give you a hint of this, to clear the truth before us.</p>
                  <p>A formal profeſſor may do much to the obſervation of others, yet it is but little of what he ought to do, if we conſider,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, that his obedience to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands does principally lie in negatives. He conſiders not ſo much what the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand requires, as what it prohibites, and he pleaſes himſelf rather in abſtaining from evil, then in doing of good, in being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, then in being renewed; he thinks it enough that he turns from ſin, though he turn not to God; this is the firſt thing ſuch a man looks to, as the Phariſee, I thank God <hi>I</hi> am not as other men.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If he looke to the preceptive part of the command, he is low and carnal in this; for he does not look to the ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Law; thus the Phariſes did, and the Papiſts do, who taught the people to be zealous of ſome few things, but neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected many more then they taught. In ſomuch that Chriſt told the people, that if <hi>their righteouſneſs did not exceed the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſes, they ſhould in no wiſe enter into the kingdom of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:170271:68"/>
                  <p>That which is the reaſon of his falling ſhort in both theſe, is this; he takes the common ſenſe vvhich men put upon the commands of God, and obſerving them in their ſenſe, he ſeems to do much; but in the ſenſe vvhich God puts upon the word, he does nothing; thus vvhile <hi>Paul</hi> vvalked by the interpretation of the commands which the Phariſees did put upon them, he in his own account is blameleſs. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.6. but vvhen he began to ſee the ſpirituality of the law, and to look upon it in the ſenſe and meaning of the ſpirit, then <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Sin revived, and he dyed.</hi> While vve look upon the command of God vvith a carnal and common eye, there is little du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty diſcovered thereby; but let us look aright upon it, and every command vvil convince of much ſin, and diſcover much duty: much more ſin then many are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd of, and much more duty then they ſubmit unto, and then vve ſhall ſee that they omit more duty then they perform. <hi>I</hi> will give you an inſtance in one command. <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other gods before me.</hi> Such men think that nothing is condemned here but Atheiſme, to have no God at all, or idolatry in worſhipping of ſtocks &amp; ſtones, not minding that theſe things are condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as ſins againſt this command;</p>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:170271:68"/>
                  <p n="1">1. Ignorance of God: for how can we have him as our God, whom we know not?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Unbelief: if we know him, and do not believe what he ſpeaks by promiſe, or by threats; for when we fly from the word of God, and go to any thing elſe to help us, we make a god, and ſay, It is ſafer to rely here then there; and when we do not fear the threat, but run to this or that ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, we make that our god, as if we could be defended from the power &amp; juſtice of God.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Want of love to God, or not loving him ſutable to himſelf: to acknowledge him to be God, and not to love him, is a contradiction: and to ſay we love him, and yet not to love him intenſly with all our hearts, and with all our might, is not to love him as our God.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The over-loving of any creature: this is the ſetting up of another <hi>god;</hi> when we ſet up any thing in our affections, and in our eſteem in the higheſt place, this is the ſetting up of another god, becauſe we ſet up ſomething in the place of <hi>God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Pride of ſpirit: ſetting up too high an eſteem of our ſelves, and of our own wiſdom or righteouſneſs; this is the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up of another god; therefore <hi>David</hi> layes the reaſon of neglecting <hi>God</hi> and his worſhip here; <hi>Pſalm</hi> 10.4. out of the
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170271:69"/>pride of their heart, they wil not ſeek after God.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Carnal joy: to delight in any thing ſo much as in God, and his worſhip and ways, is idolatry alſo. That which brings in moſt comfort is our god: if God wil ever be a Heaven to us, his worſhip and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice muſt be our Heaven here.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Luke-warmneſs in his ſervice: for to have no God, and to worſhip him as if he were none, is all one; and to ſet up a god of ſilver or ſtone, or to worſhip God as if he were no better, and knew not the heart, are things of the ſame import.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Slightneſs of ſpirit: which is when either we ſuffer our hearts and thoughts to wander we know not, and care not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and think not upon God, or when we think ſlightly of him; the firſt of theſe <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> obſerves as a ſufficient ground of the Atheiſme of many in his time, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 10.4. God is not in all his thoughts; and God himſelf ſeems to take ſpecial notice of the ſecond, and threatens ſore for it, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 50.21. thou thoughteſt that I was altogether ſuch a one as thy ſelf.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Neglect of ſeeking God: this is a great breach of this command; publique and private neglect of this duty. God puts thoſe men amongſt the heathens him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170271:69"/>
                     <hi>Jer.</hi> 10.25, <hi>Pour out thy fury upon the heathen that know thee not, and upon the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies that call not on thy Name.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. Unthankfulneſs for mercy received; this is a principle in the light of nature that we muſt acknowledg <hi>God</hi> in all that we enjoy; therefore the heatheniſh idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters did never obtaine any great victory, or enjoy any great thing, but they did ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to, and praiſe their gods. To have a <hi>God,</hi> and not to cal upon him by prayer, and thankſgiving, not to take our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts out of his hands by the one, and put them into his hands by the other, is to ſay we have no <hi>God,</hi> and to ſay we have no need of him, which is an ungodding of him. Thus <hi>I</hi> might ſhew you in other commands how much ſin is reproved which a formaliſt is not convinc'd of; and as there is much in the negative part of this command which he ſees not; ſo there is a preceptive part which he conſiders not, which is to have <hi>God</hi> for our <hi>God,</hi> and this requires many things.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That we know <hi>God;</hi> for without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of <hi>God</hi> we cannot have him for ours.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Acknowledgment of him; we muſt own and profeſſe him to be ours, and to be what he is to us.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Beleeving in him; we muſt take his
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170271:70"/>word as the beſt aſſurance, and receive all his commands and threatnings for truth.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. To love him as the chifeſt good, and to deſire communion with him as being the chiefeſt bleſſing: for to account any thing better, or to deſire any thing like him, is not to have him for our God. We muſt ſay as <hi>David, Pſalm</hi> 73.25. <hi>Whom have I in Heaven but thee, neither have I deſired in the earth any thing in compariſon of thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. To fear him, and to tremble at his word: therefore the worſhipping of God is ſet out thus by the Prophet, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8.13. <hi>Make him your dread and your feare, Iſai.</hi> 66.2.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. We muſt delight in him above all things: for the chiefeſt good enjoyed muſt needs breed the greateſt joy that is poſſible in the hearts of the creatures.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. To be zealous for his glory: we do not ſerve him as <hi>God,</hi> unleſs we ſerve him with very intenſe affections, and ſet up his glory above all glory, and mind his honour &amp; glory as <hi>God</hi> himſelf doth mind it, who ſeeks it in every thing he doth. Theſe and many more duties are required in this command; as, To remember him at all times, to have him before your eyes in
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170271:70"/>the creatures, and our hearts in meditation; to cal upon him in all ſtreights, to be thankful to him in all enjoyments, to ſeek his favour in all conditions, and to labour to preſerve the evidences we have of it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all precious things. This is to have <hi>God</hi> for our <hi>God;</hi> thus you might ſee if I ſhould run through other commands of <hi>God,</hi> that they are exceeding broad; and that the man that ſeems to be <hi>almoſt a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian,</hi> does but little in compariſon of what he omits; the ſins which he refrains by his interpretation of the command, are few to what the command forbids, and the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which he performs, are few of thoſe which the command requires, and he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects. In this reſpect the formaliſt half<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian does leſſe then he leaves undone, becauſe he does ſome duties which lie more viſible in the Word; but ſuch as are not ſo eaſily ſeen, and generally acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged he omits; he performs publick du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which come under common obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but he omits private duties, which are more then the publick duties of a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and he abſtaines from the groſſe and publick ſins of the outward man, but makes no conſcience of the ſins of the heart, and thoughts, which are more then the ſins of the outward man.</p>
                  <pb n="128" facs="tcp:170271:71"/>
                  <p>Beſides all this, in every duty which he performs, he omits more then he performs; the duties of a chriſtian are complicated; there is no duty performed ſingly, if it be performed aright. Many things muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in the right performance of any duty; as for example, if a man comes to hear the word, there is much more required in that duty, then the bare hearing or attending to what is ſaid, or the carrying it away with us in our books, or in our memories, or the repeating of it when we come home to our families, though many do not minde thus much that hear the word; there are theſe three things eſpecially to be minded in the right performing of this duty.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To prepare for it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. To keep the heart in it.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To be careful of the word, and our hearts after it; he hath not heard the word aright that hath not heard it thus. Now in every one of theſe there are many things re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, as in preparing to it we are,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> to get our hearts affected with the pretiouſneſs of the word that we are to hear.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> to conſider, and be humble un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der our natural deadneſs and inability to profit by the word.</p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:170271:71"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> to mourn over our former un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitableneſs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fourthly,</hi> to get a ſence of the wants of our ſouls.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly,</hi> to heighten our reſolutions of cleaving unto the Lord, and to bring a full purpoſe of heart with us to the Ordinance, to ſubmit to all that <hi>God</hi> ſhal ſay. In the hearing of the word we are required,</p>
                  <p>FIRST, to ſee if our hearts be preſent.</p>
                  <p>SECONDLY, to keep <hi>God</hi> in our eye, and to make him our dread and our fear, and to get our hearts affected with the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his majeſty.</p>
                  <p>THIRDLY, to take part with every word of conviction, and to receive truth, and to ſide with it, though it ſtrike at a right eye, or a right hand.</p>
                  <p>After the hearing of the word, the duty is not ended; for then it muſt be thy care,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, to keep thoſe impreſſions alive, which the Word hath made upon thy ſoul.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, to have a ſpecial care of the bent of the heart tolabour to prevent back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, to enquire whether thou haſt profited by the Ordinance, and how.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, to cover the Word by prayer, and meditation, as the Husbandman doth the ſeed, leaſt the fowls of the aire ſteal it away.</p>
                  <pb n="130" facs="tcp:170271:72"/>
                  <p>Fifthly, to put that ſpeedily in practice which the word hath convinc'd ought to be done, or to lay that down which the word ſays muſt be left. Thus it is in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and every other duty; there are many things to be minded, and done in every duty which the half chriſtian doth not mind; and while he only looks to the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of it, and neglects all theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comitant duties, he does manifeſtly omit more then he does perform; thus it is manifeſt in the firſt ſenſe, that ſuch a man does perform leſſe then he does omit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he omits many things, and performs but few; he does little in compariſon of what he omits, if we conſider that the things which he omits are greater then thoſe which he doth perform; he is care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and ſtrict in ſome things, but they are little things; but he neglects the great and weighty things of God; as it was ſaid of the Scribes and Phariſees, they paid tith of Mint and Commin, but negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted the great and weighty matters of the Law. He omits thoſe duties which are of greateſt account, in which the life and power of godſineſs lies; he is in the form of Religion, but minds not the ſpirit and ſtrength of it, which conſiſteth not in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170271:72"/>reading, hearing, receiving of Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, giving of Alms, or abſtaining from the outward acts of it, but it lies in the frame and diſpoſition of the heart to God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in all theſe. It lies in the fearing and loving of God, beleeving and delighting in him; this is that which God eyes and values in every duty. But he that is not altogether a chriſtian, is not acquainted with theſe things; he is not acquainted with heart-examination, or watching over his thoughts, he cares not about the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of his heart aright in duties, and the exerciſing of grace in them. Now alas, when theſe things are abſtracted from du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, what are they? they are nothing in <hi>Gods</hi> account, and ſo for all his reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is very little, vvhen vve conſider it is but in the outward man; when he ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtains from the outward acts of ſin, but not from the inward; his reformation is not mortification, and alas all outward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation hath little in it in compariſon of the mortification of the leaſt ſin, ſo that if you ſet his duties againſt his neglects ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in number or vveight, it is manifeſt he doth but little to what he leaves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="demonstration">
                  <pb n="132" facs="tcp:170271:73"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>DEMONSTRATION</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p>He that is but almoſt a Chriſtian, is but little a Chriſtian, becauſe there is very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in that little he does; it is of little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and eſteem with <hi>God,</hi> nor with good men, and that upon ſeveral accounts.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, becauſe his heart is not in what he does, and that being not in it, which <hi>God</hi> cals eſpecially for, he values it not; when the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> did continue the worſhip of <hi>God,</hi> and obſervation of many things commanded, he charges them as if it had been wil-worſhip, becauſe it was not worſhip according to his will. Who hath required theſe things at your hands, ſays he, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.12.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, ſuch mens obedience wil not be owned at the laſt day, when Chriſt ſhal come and ſurvey every mans work at the great day; he wil ſay to ſuch as come with ſuch, half convictions and performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>I know you not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, there wil come a time when ſuch perſons themſelves wil be made to ſee and to acknowledge that there is but little in all that they have done when they ſhal be forc'd to cry out as the fooliſh
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170271:73"/>Virgins did, <hi>Our lamps are gone out, Mat.</hi> 25.8.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, Satan wil make but a very ſlender account of all that theſe men do, or have done; alas how eaſily wil he ſhake ſuch mens hopes and confidence, as a reed is ſhaken with the wind? In time of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation how does he batter their reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in time of ſickneſs or death? how wil he take the houſe which they have built, and pluck it down about their ears? he wil make nothing of the ſtorming of ſuch a ſoul, but wil lay their ſtrength in the duſt in a moment. This <hi>Job</hi> intimates, <hi>Job.</hi> 27.7, 8. that at ſuch a time the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites own heart wil reproach him.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, all that ſuch a man does is ſo little, that it is not worthy to be compared with the leaſt performance of a gracious heart; he that does leaſt, and does it ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, does more then he that does moſt in a way of formality; for there is more done in the leaſt act in which grace is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed, then in all thoſe things in which gifts and parts are exerciſed without grace for this is that only which makes things down-weight with <hi>God.</hi> Upon this account it was that the Lord Jeſus ſet a higher va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue upon the gift of the poor Widdow,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170271:74"/>who caſt in two mites, then upon all the great gifts of the Scribes and Phariſees.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, there is ſo little in all that is done without grace, that God accounts it worſe then nothing, he reckons it as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs: it is with God no more then the cutting off a doggs neck, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.3.</p>
                  <p>Laſt of all, how ever the profeſſion and performances of ſuch a man may ſeem great, yet they wil appeare very ſmal by that time deductions are made for what is to be deducted; do but deduct out of his performances,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſid.</hi> 1. what is done upon low carnal principles, and what is done upon baſe ends and intereſts of his own, there wil be very little left of all that he ſeems to do; as for example, <hi>Jehu</hi> went very far in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving many of the commands of God, and appeared very zealous in the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them; but by that time we abate <hi>Jehu</hi> for his own intereſt, and for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of the kingdom in his own hand, we ſhal find little left ſtanding upon the account of obedience to the command; yea when the Lord reckons up what <hi>Jehu</hi> had done by one of the Prophets with theſe deductions, he cals not what he had
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170271:74"/>done obedience, or zeal for the Lord, but murder, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.4. ſuch interpretations may thoſe actions have, which in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are good, and carry a great appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance with them of obeying and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, when they are weighed with the dreggs or droſſe of thoſe falſe principles and ends which are with thoſe that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Con.</hi> 2 If you be not Chriſtians in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, all that you do wil but aggravate your ſins; your complyance with God in ſome things wil not excuſe, but aggravate your breach with him in other things; this wil bring your ſins under other aggravating circumſtances, which other mens ſins do not fal under; your ſins wil be judged hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſies in that they were under a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and ſins againſt knowledge in that they were under convictions, and contempt of Chriſt and his ways, in as much as Chriſt came ſo near to you in the word, and yet you put him by.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſid.</hi> 3. you have the leaſt, or wil have the leaſt to ſay for your ſelves of any people. Of all men, halters in Religion wil have the leaſt excuſe. We find when the Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> dealt with the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in this caſe; they were
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170271:75"/>all ſilent before him; one man ſtrikes a whole congregation dumb when he char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges this ſin upon them; they who uſe to have their excuſes and pleas at hand in all other caſes, have none in this, 1 <hi>King</hi> 18.21. <hi>The people anſwered not a word.</hi> Of all men in the world, theſe wil be left without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe; and of all ſins, halting and luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs wil appeare in their naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. You are the greateſt diſhonour to <hi>God</hi> of any people; you diſhonour the Father, the Son, and the Spirit; for men look upon you as men ſerving and owning <hi>God,</hi> and they judge of <hi>God,</hi> and his worſhip, by you.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, you diſhonour the Father; men have low thoughts of his maieſty, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, when they ſee thoſe who go under the notion of profeſſors, and owners of the ways of <hi>God,</hi> to be ſlight and cold in his worſhip; when they ſee the ſpirits of men that worſhip <hi>God</hi> cold in it, and ſtinted, and ſhut up in ſuch and ſuch a compaſſe of profeſſion, ſetting bounds to themſelves! this and that they wil do, and no more. Oh how can men think that the God whom you have to do withall is a holy <hi>God.</hi> Oh the mean and baſe thoughts men do harbour of God, from the beholding
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170271:75"/>the luke-warme converſations of ſuch half chriſtians!</p>
                  <p>Secondly, diſhonour Chriſt and the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel under which you live; oh my friends, is it not a reproach to Chriſt, that it ſhould be ſaid, This life which you live in, is that life which Chriſt came to purchaſe, &amp; for which he layd downe his life; did Chriſt come to give life, yea and abundance of life? <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.10. and is this that life? Is that life which many of us live (who would be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted partakers of the life of Chriſt) like that life which Chriſt came to give? the Evan geliſt ſays, we receive grace for grace from him; but where is it, &amp; when it is exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed? Ah my freinds Chriſt is reproached in this, when we cal and account that the life of Chriſt, which is but an abomination to him; Nay this is a reproach to the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peltimes, in which was promiſed a greater meaſure of grace to be poured forth, and that God would give a more choice and excellent ſpirit to his people, <hi>Zachary</hi> 12.10. But do not the low and lukewarm tempers of many pretended Chriſtians bring mean thoughts upon the goſpel, and the times of it, while they live much below the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of religion in the times of the law?</p>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:170271:76"/>
                  <p n="3">3. It is a reproach to the ſpirit of <hi>God,</hi> whoſe office it is to ſanctifie and renew the heart of his people: what honour does the Scripture put upon this? it cals it <hi>The beauty of holineſs, Pſalm</hi> 110: 3. as if there were no beauty but this. Now what a vilifying of the ſpirit of <hi>God</hi> is it, to ſet up a dead, cold, heartleſſe profeſſion without life and vigour inſtead of the ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifying work of the Spirit of <hi>God?</hi> as if we ſhould ſay, Loe this is all that the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit works in the hearts of <hi>Gods</hi> people. Doubtleſs it is from hence that men and women have ſuch meane and low thoughts of ſanctification, becauſe they ſee ſo little in the lives of thoſe that profeſs it, and many do believe that it is nothing but a pretence and a ſhadow, and a notion taken up amongſt men; and if they do but go to Church ſometimes, and ſay their prayers, and beleeve as the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves, they are as much ſanctified as any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for they ſee no more in others then in themſelves, but that ſome can talk more then they. Thus I ſay the Father, the Son, and the Spirit, they are all vilified, and all by reaſon of thoſe who cal themſelves chriſtians, but are not; and if there be a woe to that man by whom offences come, then much more woe to thoſe men by whom all theſe offences come.</p>
                  <pb n="139" facs="tcp:170271:76"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſ.</hi> 5. You are the greateſt blots to religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the world: All the Apoſtaſies of Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors which have hardened many mens hearts againſt Religion, have riſen from the midſt of you: There was never an Apoſtate in the world, but he was firſt a luke-warm profeſſor. Look to all the groſs and damnable errors which have broken forth, and the horrible Apoſtaſies which have been from the profeſſion of the truth, and they ſprung up amongſt thoſe who have been halters with <hi>God;</hi> Some that have ſeemingly, and in part received the truth, but have not received it in the love of it. Theſe are the people which <hi>God</hi> hath given up to ſtrong deluſions, and are ſwept away vvith abominable er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and theſe have fallen away in time of temptation, becauſe they were not rooted and grounded in the truth; but there was never any one did Apaſtatize and fal away wholly and fully from the truth that was altogether a Chriſtian. If you would not be Apoſtates from the truth, pray that your hearts may be ſound in the ſtatutes of the Lord, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119.80.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſid.</hi> 6. You are men upon whom the Devil hath the greateſt advantage of any men in the world; he chooſes you out as inſtruments to carry on all his great
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170271:77"/>works, and to further his grand deſignes in the world; by your help it is, that he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages all the affairs of his kingdom: it is a dreadful thing to think that you ſhould be the chief pillars of Satans throne; he cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes not out the prophane, becauſe they are too groſs, they wil be eaſily diſcovered; he cannot eaſily engage the godly, becauſe they wil diſcover him: the firſt he uſes not becauſe they are not ſo fit for his work; the ſecond he cannot engage, becauſe they do not like his work; but when he cannot ſpeed any where elſe, then he comes to you the formaliſt and luke-warm profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, who never fails him; but amongſt theſe he finds inſtruments enough, and thoſe he moſt uſes for his tranſactions; therefore the devil made uſe of <hi>Judas,</hi> and of the falſe brethren in the Churches, and of the Scribes and Phariſes againſt <hi>Christ,</hi> and the devout women againſt <hi>Paul, Gal.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.15. he uſes theſe rather then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> becauſe theſe are moſt able to hurt the people of God, knowing their ways and counſels as the falſe brethren did, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.26.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> becauſe their oppoſition to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion ſeems to carry in it ſome weight, and reaſon, and men judge there is ſome
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170271:77"/>great evil in it which theſe men ſee, or they would never oppoſe. The Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees would not ſo oppoſe as they do, if they did not ſee more evil in theſe things then we do, <hi>John</hi> 7.48. <hi>Have any of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, or of the Phariſees beleeved on him?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> it is greater reproach to religion and to the profeſſors of it, when the devil can ingage ſome againſt it that have profeſt it: as the Lord wounds the kingdome of Sathan by converſion: ſo doth Satan wound the kingdom of Chriſt by tempting men to Apoſtaſy.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. You are the greateſt hinderers of the ſalvation of other men; for many have their eyes upon you, and they reaſon thus with themſelves; theſe men are wiſe men, and civil men, they are good men, and wil be wary, they know what they do, and we wil follow them, we wil go no farther then they go. Many more that wil not take a Drunkard, or prophane Swearer for example in Religion, wil take one of you for a preſident, whom he ſees to walk civilly, and morally in your converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and perhaps he wil give more heed to you, becauſe of your wiſdom and warineſs in the world, then to thoſe who walk more cloſe with God; as we ſee the people looked more to the Scribes and Phariſees then
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170271:78"/>to Chriſt, and it was not the Publican that kept off ſo many from Chriſt, but the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee; ſo I ſay that wo may fall upon you which was pronounc'd againſt them, and it is a fearful one, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.11. becauſe they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enterd into the kingdom of heaven themſelves nor yet ſuffered thoſe who were entring in to go in.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſ.</hi> 8. You are a people of whom the Lord ſpeaks no good, God is ſo tender that he will not paſs by any good where ever he finds it; if it be never ſo ſmall, he will not paſs it over without obſervation; yet when he ſpeaks of ſuch as you are, he cannot afford them one good word; we find the Lord who will not break the bruiſed reed, nor quench the ſmoaking flax, would take notice of ſome good that was in <hi>Abijah</hi> who was of <hi>Jeroboams</hi> houſe. 1. <hi>King.</hi> 14.13. when he comes to ſpeak of the Church of <hi>Laodicea</hi> who was of this lukewarme tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, he ſpeaks never a word in commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17. She had high thoughts of herſelf, but God thought not ſo of her. He reproves the reſt of the Churches for their ſins and threatens ſore, but he commends ſome good in every one except <hi>Laodicea;</hi> thus <hi>I</hi> ſay the Lord wil ſpeak no good of you; you may perhaps think as
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170271:78"/>highly of your ſelves as ſhe did, but at the laſt day are like to hear the worſt of your ſelves of any generation of men whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſ.</hi> 9. God doth not only ſpeak no good of them, but they are of all ſorts of men moſt deſpiſed of him, We uſe to ſay he is poor that God hates; ſurely then the half Chriſtian is a poor man; if ther be any one poor under heaven, for no man carries ſuch a brand of infamy and reproach upon him as he doth. God does abominate ſuch a man more then he does the prophane <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau,</hi> or the ſcoffing <hi>Iſmael,</hi> or the unclean <hi>Sodomites;</hi> men that are down right A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, or plain Idalators, or that have no pretences to the fear or ſervice of God are not ſuch an abhorring to God as theſe men are? I will convince you by two, or three in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of this, that you may ſee and fear to reſt in ſuch a ſtate as this is; ſee ſuch a temper compared with him who has no religion at all, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.15. <hi>I know thy works, that thou are neither cold nor hot, I would thou wert cold or hot,</hi> God wiſhes they were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtark cold. God had rather men had no pretence to religion at all, that they were ſtupid, and had no life nor mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at all, then to move thus; better be
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170271:79"/>without ſenſe, then not to have a true ſenſe; better have no convictions nor ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings under the Word, nor pretence to love or fear God, then not to be in good earneſt; better to do nothing, then to ſtick at any thing. Now this muſt needs be a ſad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion which <hi>God</hi> diſlikes rather then no profeſſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> ſee it compared with idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, which of all ſins which do openly ſhew themſelves, does moſt affront God to his face; and therefore the Lord threatens the ſetting up of Idols in his jealouſie, in the ſecond Commandement; the Drunkard, the Swearer, the unclean perſon, do not ſo openly oppoſe God as the Idolater, becauſe he does manifeſtly ungod him. But he that is a down-right idolater, is not ſo bad as he that is a halter in the worſhip of <hi>God;</hi> the Prophet complains of the preſent tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they did <hi>halt betwixt two opinions,</hi> they would not cleave to <hi>Baal,</hi> nor yet to God, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 18.21. And <hi>Elijah ſaid unto all the people, How long halt ye between two opinions? If the LORD be God, follow him; but if Baal, then follow him:</hi> ſo it may be ſaid to the half Chriſtian, why do you halt betwixt a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and God? to have a heart divided be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and corruption, is worſe then to ſerve ſin with all the heart.</p>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:170271:79"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> ſee it compared with open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs; we find the ſervant who did but comply with the wicked and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, in eating and drinking with them that were drunken, yet threatned more then all the reſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.49, 50, 51. <hi>The lord of that ſervant ſhall come in a day when he loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not for him, and in an hour that he is not ware of, and ſhall cut him aſunder, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point him his portion with the hypocrites: there ſhal be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi> He did not caſt off his ſubjection to his maſter al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together; he ſaid not that he had no maſter, neither did he caſt off the thoughts of his maſters coming, but he removed them a little from him; and when he had done this, we do not find that he was a drunkard, but he began to aſſociate with them, he began to neglect his duty, and to comply vvith the prophane whom he ſhould have cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed; and now the Lord paſſes by them, and ſeems to take leſs notice of their open wickedneſs, then of his ſecret comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with it; thus it is with many who wil not be, or dare not be Swearers, or Drunkards, but they wil keep a hand for the drunkard, or the ſcoffer, they will be the friends and familiar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> with ſuch in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret; they have not gotten ſo much zeal for God, and for his ways, as to deſpiſe a
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170271:80"/>vile perſon, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 15.4. but ſuch as theſe God complains of by the Prophet, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 7.8. <hi>Iſrael was a cake not turned;</hi> if you look upon their outſide, they were Chriſtians; but if you could ſee the <hi>inſide,</hi> they were idolaters. Such God wil ſpue out of his mouth, with the greateſt loathing poſſible; he does moſt commonly caſt them out of their profeſſion here, and out of their Church-priviledges if they be under any, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.19. or if not here, when he comes to judgement, he will ſurely remember theſe; they ſhal be caſt out before men and Angels, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.51. <hi>they ſhall have their portion with hypocrites, there ſhal be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth;</hi> theſe ſhal have a place in hel by themſelves, the prophaneſt ſort of men wil hiſs them out of their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the devils will ſtand off from them, becauſe they ſeemed to be diſtinct from them in the world; and as for the godly, they ſhal be ſeparated from them, becauſe they were not of them. Thus theſe hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites ſhal have a place by themſelves, and if any worſe then other, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>al be theirs. As of all ſorts of ſinners, theſe are the worſt, becauſe hypocrites: ſo of all kinde of hypocrites, theſe are worſt. It is a great miſtake amongſt the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who think none are hypocrites but
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170271:80"/>they which make ſome extraordinary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Religion, they judge them to be hypocrites; and them onely who make a greater profeſſion then the common ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard (by which the multitude meaſure their Religion) will allow of: ſo that none are reckoned for hypocrites, but thoſe who are noted for profeſſors. This I ſay is a great miſtake; for there is not a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man or woman in this place, how pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſoever, but is an hypocrite, for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one here does profeſs himſelf a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; and if it be not ſo, he is an hypocrite; there is not one here that wil renounce all intereſt in Chriſt, or that will openly in words refuſe obedience to him, yea there is not one here but does at ſome times, in ſome wayes profeſſe a ſubjection to him, and ſhall therefore at the laſt, not onely be condemned with the prophane, for ſaying Chriſt ſhall not reign over them, but they ſhall be judged with the Hypocrite for ſaying that they go when they go not, as the evil ſon, <hi>Matthew</hi> 21.30. who added a lie to his diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. But although amongſt them that call themſelves Chriſtians; there be many kindes of hypocrites, and all that take the name of Chriſtian upon them, are either
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170271:81"/>Saints or hypocrites, yet theſe which are <hi>almoſt Chriſtians,</hi> are the worſt of hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites; he that is <hi>almoſt a Chriſtian</hi> is of the higheſt form of hypocrites; the higher a man riſes in profeſſion, if it be not in truth, the higher he ariſes in hypocriſie; for he that does not follow God fully, when he is at the height, he is but <hi>almoſt a Christian,</hi> and that is but a raiſed piece of hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; and when a man is in this condition, this is his miſery, that all his profeſſion does but increaſe his ſin, he is ſo much the more an elaborate hypocrite. Of all perſons Chriſt cries out againſt theſe in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; how often does he cry out, Woe to <hi>you Scribes and Phariſees, Hypocrites?</hi> for all the people of the Jews by virtue of their profeſſion were ſuch, who did not obey the truth. But theſe did excel in profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they went beyond others in many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, and yet did not love the truth vvith all their hearts, therefore he cries out more againſt the Scribes and Phariſees, hypo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crites, then againſt the Publicans and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots, Hypocrites, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.13, 14, 15 23, 25 Chriſt did not cry out againſt theſe for Hypocrites for doing more then others, but for not doing vvhat they ought to do; Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie lies not in making more profeſſion then vve ought, but in doing leſs then vve
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170271:81"/>do profeſs. Therefore although he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned their hypocriſie, yet he commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their profeſſion, and ſet people to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate and exceed them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept your righteouſneſſe exceed the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees, ye cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſ.</hi> 10. Theſe are the greateſt deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of God, of Heaven, and holineſs, of any people; theſe bring the greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon the kingdom of Heaven of any, becauſe they come in ſight of it, and then go back, which is a manifeſt contempt. God was more angry with the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for talking of returning back to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> when they were in the widerneſs, then for all their unwillingneſs to come out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Nay, he was more offended at their unwillingneſs to go into <hi>Canaan,</hi> when they came upon the borders of it, then for all their murmuring at the red ſea, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when they had ſeen the fruit of it; this was a manifeſt contempt of the good land; for if they ſhould have gone back after they came ſo near unto <hi>Canaan,</hi> it would have broughtmore diſcredit upon that land then if they had never ſtirr'd out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> for if they had refuſed to go out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> all men would have imputed it to their idleneſs; but if they had returned, the
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170271:82"/>fault would have been laid upon the land. If a man paſſes by your ſhops, and inquires not for any commodity, you take little no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of him; but if he ſee your goods and cheapen them, and leave them, he either condemns the commodity or the ſeller, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is not good, or it is too dear: So men that look not after Heaven, do but neglect it; but thoſe who come to buy, and yet will not come up to the terms, theſe diſcredit it. When men come ſo neer it as the young man did, who was offered it, and yet left it when there was but one thing lacking, theſe do bring the greateſt diſlike upon the things of God, of any men alive; for theſe men do in effect ſay, it is not ſo much worth; they ſay that God offers it at too dear a rate; and what greater reproach can there be caſt upon the kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: then to ſay it is too dear? The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſort of men do but neglect it, they never ask after it, they cheapen not; but the half Chriſtian he ſees and asks, and cheapens, but will not buy; this is a villify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it. This is your caſe, you that are almoſt chriſtians; you wil bee found the greateſt contemners of the ways of God; for other men fall ſhort out of ignorance, as having not ſeen or known God; but you come oftentimes ſo neer, that you ſee
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:170271:82"/>the kingdom of God, as <hi>Baalam</hi> did whoſe eyes were opened, you taſt of the powers of the World to come, you are made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the Holy Ghoſt, and have found a ſweetneſs in the good Word of God; for you now to ſtop here, or go back again, it muſt needs bee a contemning of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; you ſay as that young man did. There is not ſo much worth in the ſame to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervail the loſſe of all other things, Chriſt wil put that interpretation upon your mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which he did upon the Jews, <hi>John</hi> 15.24. For you have ſeen and hated both me and my Father. The ſins of ignorant perſons are accounted but neglect, but the ſins of ſuch as are convinc'd, will be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hating of God; becauſe ſuch do know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly caſt away the offers of the Goſpel, and refuſe the kingdom of God, and their refuſing is not a bare neglecting to receive it, but a deſpiſing of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſid.</hi> 11. <hi>Such men have the leaſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of any.</hi> They ſtand betwixt the <hi>plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the World,</hi> and the <hi>pleaſures of the Saints,</hi> and enjoy neither. Such a man cannot ſhare with the Epicure in the pleaſures of the fleſh, becauſe of his convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; theſe give a check to his luſts; ſo that hee cannot take that liberty that his heart
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170271:83"/>doth deſire; his unhappineſs is that his heart is not <hi>mortified to the love of ſin, yet he is dead to the pleaſure of ſin;</hi> that which is ſweet to others is bitter to him; not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he loves it not, but becauſe he finds ſome gnawing of the worm of Conſcience, which will not let him bee quiet in his luſts. If he go to the Ale-houſe, he ſits un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſily there, becauſe Conſcience accuſes him; if he goes not thither, he is not qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, becauſe his heart is there. In the midſt of his laughter, there is heavineſs in his heart; in his ſinfull pleaſures he is ſad, and enjoys not what others do, or what he has done in former times: Time was, he could hearken to his carnal appetite in any thing and it was pleaſant to him; but it is not ſo now; conſcience either reſtrains him from the ſin he loves, and this cannot pleaſe him, or elſe it withholds from him the pleaſure of the ſin he commits, and this muſt needs be ſad. Beſide this, he loſeth the pleaſure of duty, if Conſcience puts him upon any duty, he loſes alſo the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of that, becauſe it is not performed with an upright heart; he wants a new na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to make the duty pleaſant unto him; he wants holy and ſpiritual affections in it, to make him delight in his work; and although in ſome Ordinances he may have
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170271:83"/>ſome flaſhes of joy, yet he wants that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſpiritual comfort and refreſhing which Gods people have in the ſervice and worſhip of God; he cannot ſay that his chiefeſt joy lies in his duties; he cannot ſay as <hi>David,</hi> that God puts more this way into his heart then when Corn and Wine increaſeth, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 4.7. Nay, we find that this may be, and is the frame of ſuch as find no comfort in following God, that they are burthened with duty; the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> who delighted to approach unto God, as we find <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.2. they ſeek me daily and delight to know my ways, yet ſaid, When will the Sabbath be over? <hi>Am.</hi> 8.5. And ſuch as theſe do often upon this account Apoſtatize from the wayes of God, and then they do reproach them moſt of any perſons, as thoſe hypocrites did, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.14, who ſaid It is in vain to ſerve God. Now lay theſe things together, and ſee in what a ſad caſe theſe men are; they have neither the pleaſures of the wicked, nor of the godly: Wicked men have their good things here, the godly have their good things hereafter. <hi>The wicked ſeem to have one Heaven, the godly hath ſometimes two</hi> (a Heaven of peace and joy in the Holy ghoſt here, and a Heaven hereafter alſo) <hi>but the half Chriſtian hath no Heaven,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170271:84"/>here nor hereafter. <hi>The open prophane have one heaven the godly two, the hypoerite none.</hi> ſo that it may be ſaid of them truly that they are of all men moſt miſerable be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their hope and comfort is onely in this life, and yet it is nothing conſiderable to other mens.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſid.</hi> 12. <hi>Such men as theſe do loſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to all parties.</hi> They are eſteemed of by none, though they deſigne to be hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all. Firſt of all they loſe their cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit and repute with their old companions by their profeſſion. That reformation which they have made already, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps make the profaner and looſer ſort caſt them off as not fitt for them. And although they diſpiſe them for their profeſſion, yet the godly will not heartly embrace them they are as much diſ-ſatisfyed with their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, that it is no more, as the other are troubled that it is ſo much. Thus they are caſt off by their old friends before they are received of the new, and by this meanes they are deſtitute of both. The prophane ſort think they are too ſtrict for them, and the godly ſuſpect they are too large for them; they are too hot for the one, and too cold for the other; one thinks he looks too like a Puritan, and the other
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:170271:84"/>doubts he is too much a formaliſt, and upon this account he is deſerted of both; like the Bat, which is in the body like a Mouſe, and yet winged like a bird, is excluded from the ſociety both of Birds and Beaſts. They are plac'd betwixt the godly and the wicked, as ſome Divines have drawn <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> Picture, betwixt Heaven and Hell, not knowing in which to place him. If they ſhould be placed among the prophane they would be offended, having eſcaped the corruptions of the World through Luſt; and if you place them among the Godly, you ſhould wrong the generation of the juſt. I knew in my time in the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity three Doctors heads of houſes,</p>
                  <p>One was an Innovator.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond accounted a Puritan.</p>
                  <p>The third was reckon'd a Neuter. A witty Scholler preſented them thus.</p>
                  <p>The firſt in a Coach driving to <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond driving to <hi>Genevah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The third running on foot, begging ſometimes the one, ſometimes the other to receive him, yet both refuſing. Such are theſe Neuters in Religion, leſt out by all. All thoſe which are but
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170271:85"/>almoſt chriſtians, are but Neuters at the beſt. They are not what they were, and they are not what they would ſeem to be; and ſo being of neither kind, they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed of both. It is hard for any man to make any profeſſion of a change without troubling the prophaner part of men; and it is as hard for any man that is not truly changed, to make ſuch a profeſſion as to pleaſe the godly. The people of <hi>God</hi> will find out their cold formal ſpirits, under the moſt zealous profeſſion that may be; that profeſſion muſt be very handſomly put on, that muſt cover the old unregenerate heart for a time; but if it ſhould do ſo, it is not like to hide it long from the eys of Gods people; and when this is once diſcovered, there is no greater abhorring to them.</p>
                  <p>The Neuter ſtill hath leaſt friends, ſo hath the half Chriſtian. Hee is deſpiſed by the prophane, rejected of the godly, and loved heartily of none.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſid.</hi> 13. <hi>Such people are in greateſt danger of being hardned of any.</hi> The light and knowledge which they have, together with the profeſſion which they make, does but darken them, and thereby they are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fool'd into a good opinion of themſelves, and reſt quiet in their ſuppoſed good eſtate until the day of wrath comes upon them
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170271:85"/>unawares: There is more hope of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting a prophane wretch, then a formal profeſſour. For a man hath more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage upon ſuch a one, having ſomething more to take hold of in him, then in the other. If a man deal with a drunkard, ſwearer, or unclean perſon, you have his natural light, common received principles, and his conſcience to take hold of, which will all take part with you in this caſe: But natural light, common principles and natural conſcience will not ſerve to detect this man, they will all rather riſe up and plead his cauſe. For a little profeſſion and weak performances ſerve to quiet the Conſcience, and make it lie down well ſatisfied. Him that Conſcience would not ſuffer to be quiet in an Ale-houſe, nor in the pollutions of the World, yet may be quiet in the performance of ſome duties, though they be done without the exerciſe of any grace. It is harder to faſten a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction upon ſuch mens ſpirits, then upon any others, becauſe their ſins lie more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and are hid from the eys of men; yea and therefore from the light of their own conſciences. Hence it is that the Lord makes the conviction of unbelief ſo great a work <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.7.8. he ſaies the ſpirit ſhould come to convince of this. Natural conſcience
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170271:86"/>does convince of drunkenneſs and ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, of idolatry and uncleaneſs, but it doth not convince of unbelief, becauſe this is a ſin of the heart. Nay, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelief is not always alike eaſie to be detected, it is more eaſily diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered when it lies under prophaneſs, then when it lies under profeſſion;</hi> it is eaſier to convince a drunkard unbeleever, or an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean unbeleever, then a praying unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; becauſe his unbelief lies more curiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hid, and is where we would not expect. Hence it is that the Scribes and Phariſees were ſo handly convinc'd, and ſo few of them were converted by the preaching of the Goſpel; yea the Publicans and the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots entred into the kingdom of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; when the word took hold of the Publicans and Harlots they confeſt their ſins and were humbled, but the Scribes and Phariſes juſtified themſelves; Conſcience accuſed one, and excuſed the other; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore one was convinced and converted, but the other was lifted up and hardned.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Conſid.</hi> 14. He that is but almoſt a chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, is in a ſad condition, becauſe of the miſerable diſappointments of the laſt day: doubtleſs this is one of the woes pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt thoſe who are lifted up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and from thence caſt down to Hell. To fall from ſuch hopes and confidence, and
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170271:86"/>preſumptions, as many half chriſtians have, to a ſtate of miſery (as much below other men, as their hopes were above theirs) muſt needs bee an extremity of miſery, to fall down a precipice, from an expectation and aſſurance of happineſs, to be plunged in endleſs and remedileſs grief, &amp; horror; this muſt needs be a double Hell. Theſe are the men and women that have puniſhment of loſs as well as ſenſe. The puniſhment of loſs is nothing ſo conſiderable to other men, as it is to them. For, for a man to loſe that which he neither had, nnr hoped for, nor cared for, is but ſmall to what it is to him that hoped it, attempted it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded himſelf in a manner poſſeſs'd of it. A man that never meant to go to Sea, nor cared for merchandizing, laments not that he hath not the riches of the <hi>Indies,</hi> becauſe he never ſtudied for, nor indeavour'd it. But the Merchant that victuals &amp; mans his ſhip, and goes along voyage and fails of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in the very Continent, or that is taken comming back, or is forc'd to caſt all over board in a ſtorm, when he is within ſight of his own ſhore, hee is tormented with this loſs, feels it, and ſmarts under it. The very loſs of ſuch a mans hopes, is as great an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction as can befal him. Thus doubtleſſe the bare loſs of Heaven, will be a Hell to the half Chriſtian, and will fill his
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170271:87"/>ſoul with inconceivable ſorrow. Beſide the puniſhment of his hypocriſie (which ſhal increaſe his paine) he ſhal be more exquiſitely tortured with the ſenſe of his loſſe then other men, which wil be like a gnawing Worm continually afflicting his ſoul, and, wil be as bad, if not vvorſe, then all the devils can inflict upon him. Was it not think you a ſad aggravation of the miſery of the fooliſh Virgins, (vvho kept company all their days with the wiſe) to be ſeparated from them, and to be recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the tranſgreſſors? Oh were they not in hel in their ſpirits, as ſoon as they ſaw their Lamps gone out? what a darkneſs was then upon the face of their ſouls? ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter darkneſs, and deſpairing thoughts, blacker then any that ever covered the face of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Was not (think you) their trouble greatly increaſed by the acceſſion of this evil unto the reſt, that this was an un looked for grief? they roſe to trim their lamps with confidence of being able to walk by the light of their Lamps, as well as the other. But when they came to the door, and found that ſhut againſt them, and cryd, Lord, Lord, and had no other language, but I know you not; how do you think their hearts could hold any longer? Did they not now break, and did they not
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:170271:87"/>now begin to beat their wretched breaſts faſter then they had beaten at the door, and lament themſelves, wiſhing that they could but find any place to hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from his power, who could not get into his favour? And all this being carried back to their former condition, muſt needs afflict them; they a few hours ſince had their Lamps burning, and ſhops open, where they might have bought oil for their veſſels; but now their Lamps are gone out, and the ſhops are all ſhut, and no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion is laid up, nor none to be gotten for eternity.</p>
                  <p>Oh it was not many hours ſince, that they had ſtrong hopes of being ſaved, but now they have none; <hi>Oh now they wiſh they had that hope again, or wiſh they had never hada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> that the remembrance of it might not torment them; but this cannot be? <hi>they can neither recover what they have loſt, nor forget what they had.</hi> What do you think is the condition of theſe poor ſouls? are not they in hel already? is it needful to caſt them into another hel? ſurely the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of loſs doth deeply afflict them, and if they ſhould be left under the bare ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of an excluſion from the kingdome of God, they would ſuffer in ſome propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the reſt of the damned; what
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170271:88"/>then will be their miſery, when they ſhall be thrown amongſt the damned and caſt into utter darkneſſe? Oh my friends think on theſe things, and take heed that this be not your caſe. <hi>I</hi> fear it will be thus with ſome of you that are here, that ſome of you will be found dead like the Levites concubine, with your hands upon the threſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold of the houſe and Kingdome of God; ſome of you that have had great convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, made great promiſes, made ſome at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts upon reformation, taken up a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and gone ſo far as to give ſome hope to others, perhaps much more to your ſelves take heed that you do not fall from this hope; if you do it will be more tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for them of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> then for you. Thus I have given you a glance of the ſad and wofull eſtate of ſuch as are almoſt Chriſtians, and though what I have ſaid may convince you, that ſuch as theſe are in a miſerable condition; yet words are too weak, and our conceptions are all too ſhallow to expreſs, or take in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible and inconceivable wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the men of this rank and order in the world: That which <hi>Francis Spira</hi> breathed out in agony of his ſoul, when he felt a Hell kindled in his conſcience, theſe
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170271:88"/>men will breath out at laſt in Hell. Oh what a fearfull thing it is (ſaid he) to be almoſt a Chriſtian.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>CONCLUSION. <hi>Some Directions how to avoid this evil temper.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt you wil ſay, How ſhal I do to avoid this evil frame and temper which you have diſcovered? what ſhall we do that we may not be half Chriſtians? <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſhut up the application of this Doctrine, with a few directions to you that deſire to be Chriſtians indeed.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Direct.</hi> If thou wouldeſt be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a chriſtian, then labour to be very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act in thy firſt works of Chriſtianity; if thou wouldeſt build high, be ſure to lay the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation wel; make a good beginning, if ever thou wouldeſt ſee a good end. It was the Lords advice to the church of <hi>Epheſus, Rev.</hi> 2.5. and there can be no better gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Do thy firſt works, labour to revive the ſenſe of ſin which thou hadſt at firſt, and call to mind how apprehenſive thou wert of thy need of Chriſt; renew thy cloſe with Chriſt, and chooſe him
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:170271:89"/>afreſh as if thou hadſt never choſen him: Be ofen in theſe firſt works; for though half chriſtians are defective in many things, yet the ground and reaſon of all their defects lies in this, that they were never right and ſound in the beginning. Their firſt works of cloſing with Chriſt, and humbling their ſouls for ſin, was never truly performed yet; and whatever is built where the foundation is weak will fall.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Direct.</hi> Study Goſpel perfection, for know God requires a perfection now under the Goſpel, as well as he did under the Law; though that perfection which the Law requires, cannot be attained now by any, yet there is another perfection ſuited to the Goſpel, and to thy ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion required (<hi>viz.</hi> Firſt a perfection of Deſire.</p>
               <p>Secondly of deſign; it is not a bare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, but of deſires combined and ſtrongly contriving to attain the end.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Of indeavours; theſe deſigns are not the bare ſecret workings of the thoughts, and the idle thoughts of the ſluggard, who would have his work done, if it could be done with thinking while he lies and ſtretches himſelf upon his bed; but theſe deſigns muſt be brought forth into act, and back'd with all the uſe of the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170271:89"/>means which may further and facilitate ſuch a work.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, There is a perfection of ſelf reſignation; though thou canſt not ſerve the Lord perfectly with any member of the body, or any faculty of the ſoul, yet thou muſt reſign all theſe to the Lord, to labour to ſerve the Lord, both actively and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vely, by and with all theſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Direct.</hi> Keep a deep and tender ſenſe of thy own failings to humble thee, and to quicken thee to look after this perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for nothing makes men ſit down ſhort of this, but pride of ſpirit, and want of a due ſearch and inquiry into their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; it was this which made <hi>Paul</hi> preſs forward, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12, 13, 14. <hi>I</hi> count not that I have yet apprehended, and ſurely, thou wilt ſo account of thy ſelf; if thou doeſt but take an account of thy daily fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; but pride of ſpirit and an overſight of our own ſpiritual wants and weakneſſes, makes us ſit down ſhort of the mark, as high conceited <hi>Laodicea</hi> did, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Direct.</hi> Bee much in eying of Jeſus Chriſt, who is thy true pattern, by whom thou art to walke, and to whom thou oughteſt to be conformed, 1 <hi>Jo.</hi> 2.6. Hee that ſays that he abides in Chriſt, ought to walk even as Chriſt walked. Nothing
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:170271:90"/>doth ſo much ſtint and ſtreighten the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of men, as the looking too low, and mean examples of holineſſe; but ſurely if we did look to the Lord Jeſus, whoſe life is layed before us ſo eminently in the word, we ſhould ſee cauſe enough to bee humbled when we are at higheſt, and not ſit down under any attainments, ſeeing we fall ſhort ſo far of him who is our pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Direct.</hi> Be ſure to make conſcience of the inward and hidden part of duties, make Conſcience of that which no eye ſees but the Lords. Men may ſee the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward acts, and the external ornaments as flouriſhes of gifts and parts, but have thou a chief care to exerciſe grace in every thing; for this is that which makes thee paſſe for a Chriſtian before God, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever makes thee ſeem ſuch before men. If thou doeſt thus, thy veſſel ſhall not be found empty at laſt, nor thou be condemned for an empty outſide profeſſor.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Direct.</hi> Never think thy ſelf enough a Chriſtian, ſo long as thou findeſt any ſo much a Chriſtian as thy ſelf. You know when men run in a race together, a man does not content himſelf to run as faſt as others, but if any comes up with him, or neer him, it makes him ſtrive, and put
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170271:90"/>forth all his ſtrength in running, that hee may keep ſtill in the head of the company, and lead the way to all. He fears if any one ſhould come up with him, that hee would take the prize from him; thus it ſhould be with a Chriſtian, who ſhould thus run, if he would obtain, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.24. not as it were to get a prize with others, but a price from all others.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, whatever thy condition be, or how great ſoever thy attainments are, yet labour to bee much more a chriſtian then thou art; if thou ſhouldeſt excel all others, yet then make it thy buſineſſe to excel thy ſelf; ſo ſhalt thou be ſure not to fall under the weight of this heavy word, which hath been ſpoken to thoſe who are but almoſt Chriſtians.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
